<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata>
	<idinfo>
		<citation>
			<citeinfo>
				<origin>Comprehensive Coastal Inventory, Virginia Institute of Marine Science</origin>
				<pubdate>2013</pubdate>
				<title>Virginia Shoreline Inventory - Access Structures </title>
				<geoform Sync="TRUE">vector digital data</geoform>
				<pubinfo>
					<pubplace>Gloucester Point, Virginia</pubplace>
					<publish>Virginia Institute of Marine Science</publish>
				</pubinfo>
				<othercit>For shoreline inventories by county, please visit  http://ccrm.vims.edu/gis_data_maps/shoreline_inventories/index.html</othercit>
				<onlink>http://ccrm.vims.edu/gis_data_maps/shoreline_inventories/index.html</onlink>
				<ftname Sync="TRUE">va_astru_2013</ftname></citeinfo>
		</citation>
		<descript>
			<abstract>
Shoreline Situation Reports (SSR) were first generated by VIMS in the 1970's to report the condition and status of the shore lands.  The SSR series were published in hardcopy on a county by county basis for each Tidewater Virginia localities.  The reports were intended to assist planners, managers, and regulators in decisions pertaining to management of coastal areas and natural resources therein.  This Shoreline Inventory report continues a process which updates and expands the earlier reports.  Data collected reports conditions surveyed in the immediate riparian zone, the bank, and along the shoreline.
This dataset is the result of combining the most recent digital shoreline inventories for Virginia.
</abstract>
			<purpose>To inventory Virginia's tidal shoreline conditions.</purpose>
			<supplinf>There are three shapefiles that are part of the Shoreline Inventory database: *_lubc, *_astru, *_sstru. The _lubc (land use and bank cover) is a linear shapefile containing data about land use, bank height, erosion, bank cover, Phragmites australis, tree fringe, canopy overhang, marsh, and beach status along the shoreline. The _sstru (shoreline structures) is a linear shapefile delineating hard structures at the shoreline (bulkhead, breakwater, dilapidated bulkhead, debris, jetty, marina, marsh toe revetment, unconventional, riprap, groin fields). The _astru (access structures) is a point shapefile with locations of docks, ramps, dilapidated docks, outfalls, and boathouses. The attributes of these three shapefiles are explained in the Entity and Attribute Information section below.
Beginning in 2012 the method of collecting data for the shoreline inventory changed. Data for marsh and Phragmites australis is no longer recorded in the *_lubc shapefile but is found in the tidal marsh inventory shapefiles. Please visit &lt;http://ccrm.vims.edu/gis_data_maps/static_maps/gis/tmi.html&gt;. </supplinf>
			<langdata Sync="TRUE">en</langdata></descript>
		<timeperd>
			<timeinfo>
				<rngdates>
					<begdate>1998</begdate>
					<enddate>2013</enddate>
				</rngdates>
			</timeinfo>
			<current>ground condition at time of survey</current>
		</timeperd>
		<status>
			<progress>Ongoing</progress>
			<update>Unknown</update>
		</status>
		<keywords>
			<theme>
				<themekt>none</themekt>
				<themekey>Shoreline conditions</themekey>
				<themekey>Riparian Land use</themekey>
				<themekey>Shoreline Inventory</themekey>
			</theme>
			<place>
				<placekt>none</placekt>
				<placekey>Virginia</placekey>
				<placekey>Chesapeake Bay</placekey>
				<placekey>Accomack County</placekey>
				<placekey>Caroline County</placekey>
				<placekey>City of Chesapeake</placekey>
				<placekey>City of Portsmouth</placekey>
				<placekey>Essex County</placekey>
				<placekey>Fairfax and City of Alexandria</placekey>
				<placekey>Gloucester County</placekey>
				<placekey>Henrico County</placekey>
				<placekey>King and Queen County</placekey>
				<placekey>King George County</placekey>
				<placekey>King William County</placekey>
				<placekey>Lancaster County</placekey>
				<placekey>Lynnhaven Bay</placekey>
				<placekey>Mathews County</placekey>
				<placekey>Middlesex County</placekey>
				<placekey>New Kent Countiy</placekey>
				<placekey>Newport News</placekey>
				<placekey>Norfolk</placekey>
				<placekey>Northampton County</placekey>
				<placekey>Northumberland County</placekey>
				<placekey>Poquoson</placekey>
				<placekey>Prince William</placekey>
				<placekey>Richmond County</placekey>
				<placekey>Stafford County</placekey>
				<placekey>Virginia Beach</placekey>
				<placekey>Westmoreland County</placekey>
				<placekey>Pagan River</placekey>
				<placekey>York County</placekey>
				<placekey>City of Suffolk</placekey><placekey>Charles City County</placekey></place>
		</keywords>
		<accconst>none</accconst>
		<useconst>These data should not be used for jurisdictional permit determinations beyond providing general shoreline condition or status information.  These data have not been surveyed to property boundaries.</useconst>
		<ptcontac>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntper>Marcia Berman</cntper>
					<cntorg>Virginia Institute of Marine Science (VIMS)</cntorg>
				</cntperp>
				<cntpos>Director of Comprehensive Coastal Inventory Program (CCI)</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>P.O. Box 1346</addrtype>
					<address>Greate Road</address>
					<city>Gloucester Point</city>
					<state>Virginia</state>
					<postal>23062</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>804-684-7188</cntvoice>
				<cntfax>804-684-7179</cntfax>
				<cntemail>marcia@vims.edu</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</ptcontac>
		<native Sync="TRUE">Microsoft Windows Vista Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.1.3500</native><spdom><bounding><westbc Sync="TRUE">-77.460521</westbc><eastbc Sync="TRUE">-75.328685</eastbc><northbc Sync="TRUE">38.850606</northbc><southbc Sync="TRUE">36.530380</southbc></bounding><lboundng><leftbc Sync="TRUE">286401.712300</leftbc><rightbc Sync="TRUE">470584.893143</rightbc><bottombc Sync="TRUE">4045425.983700</bottombc><topbc Sync="TRUE">4300252.919623</topbc></lboundng></spdom><natvform Sync="TRUE">Shapefile</natvform></idinfo>
	<dataqual>
		<attracc>
			<attraccr>The attributes were compared to original GPS data logs for accuracy.  Errors were corrected where noted.</attraccr>
		</attracc>
		<complete>This inventory targets tidal shoreline only. Access by boat is required for field surveys. Remote sensing techniques are used in areas where water depths are too shallow for access or where unmanaged, undeveloped shoreline persists along very long reaches. This would include headwaters of tidal creeks, and natural areas along park and conservation lands.</complete>
		<posacc>
			<horizpa>
				<horizpar>Shoreline attributes recorded with a GPS unit as the boat moves along the shoreline has a horizontal accuracy of +/- 5 meters. Data was transferred from the GPS boat track to an existing digital shoreline coverage by projecting data to the shoreline at a 90 degree angle from the boat track. Rectified imagery were used as a background coverage to aid in data positioning. Land use features were placed along the shore so changes in land use were coincident with changes illustrated in the imagery. Positional accuracy for data that has been corrected with imagery which has a resolution of 2 meters or better. Accuracy limits of the field collected data, however, are set at 5 meters due to the short occupancy of GPS units. In many cases the image correction yields a final positional accuracy much closer to 2 meters or less, depending on image resolution.</horizpar>
			</horizpa>
		</posacc>
		<lineage>
			<srcinfo>
				<srccite>
					<citeinfo>
						<origin>Comprehensive Coastal Inventory Program, Virginia Institute of Marine Science</origin>
						<pubdate>1991</pubdate>
						<title>Mean High Water Shoreline Position, Virginia</title>
						<geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
					</citeinfo>
				</srccite>
				<srcscale>24,000</srcscale>
				<typesrc>mylar</typesrc>
				<srctime>
					<timeinfo>
						<rngdates>
							<begdate>1964</begdate>
							<enddate>1987</enddate>
						</rngdates>
					</timeinfo>
					<srccurr>date of USGS map</srccurr>
				</srctime>
				<srccitea>SHL</srccitea>
				<srccontr>Digital shoreline serves as base shoreline for shoreline conditions for the following counties: King and Queen, King William, and Middlesex.</srccontr>
			</srcinfo>
			<srcinfo>
				<srccite>
					<citeinfo>
						<origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
						<pubdate>1994</pubdate>
						<title>Digital Orthophoto Quadrangles</title>
						<geoform>remote-sensing image</geoform>
						<pubinfo>
							<pubplace>Reston, VA</pubplace>
							<publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
						</pubinfo>
					</citeinfo>
				</srccite>
				<typesrc>color infra-red digital imagery</typesrc>
				<srctime>
					<timeinfo>
						<sngdate>
							<caldate>1994</caldate>
						</sngdate>
					</timeinfo>
					<srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
				</srctime>
				<srccitea>DOQQ</srccitea>
				<srccontr>Serves as a background coverage in some of the map portfolios. Used to accurately position land use and cover data. Used to create a new digital shoreline coverage that serves as the base shoreline for shoreline conditions. Counties that used this shoreline: Accomack, Caroline, Essex, Lancaster, Northumberland, Richmond, and Pagan River. Counties that used this in conjunction with another shoreline: Gloucester, King and Queen, King George, King William, Middlesex, New Kent, and Newport News.</srccontr>
			</srcinfo>
			<srcinfo>
				<srccite>
					<citeinfo>
						<origin>City of Norfolk</origin>
						<pubdate>1999</pubdate>
						<title>Norfolk Hydrology</title>
						<geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
						<pubinfo>
							<pubplace>Norfolk, VA</pubplace>
							<publish>City of Norfolk</publish>
						</pubinfo>
					</citeinfo>
				</srccite>
				<typesrc>digital orthophotographs</typesrc>
				<srctime>
					<timeinfo>
						<sngdate>
							<caldate>1999</caldate>
						</sngdate>
					</timeinfo>
				</srctime>
				<srccitea>City of Norfolk</srccitea>
				<srccontr>Provided the base shoreline for the City of Norfolk</srccontr>
			</srcinfo>
			<srcinfo>
				<srccite>
					<citeinfo>
						<origin>Commonwealth of Virginia, through Virginia Geographic Network Division of its Department of Technology Planning (VGIN)</origin>
						<pubdate>2003</pubdate>
						<title>Virginia Base Map Program (VBMP)</title>
						<geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
						<pubinfo>
							<pubplace>Richmond, VA</pubplace>
							<publish>Virginia Geographic Information Network</publish>
						</pubinfo>
					</citeinfo>
				</srccite>
				<srcscale>4800</srcscale>
				<typesrc>DVD</typesrc>
				<srctime>
					<timeinfo>
						<sngdate>
							<caldate>2002</caldate>
						</sngdate>
					</timeinfo>
				</srctime>
				<srccitea>VBMP 2002</srccitea>
				<srccontr>Imagery (2002) serves as a background in the map portfolio. Imagery is used to update land use and structure data as well as to remotely code areas not previously surveyed in the field.  The VBMP shoreline was also used and adjusted using the imagery where needed. This shoreline was used in the following counties: Gloucester, Lynnhaven Bay, Stafford, and Westmoreland.</srccontr>
			</srcinfo>
			<srcinfo>
				<srccite>
					<citeinfo>
						<origin>Commonwealth of Virginia, through Virginia Geographic Network Division of its Department of Technology Planning (VGIN)</origin>
						<pubdate>2006/2007</pubdate>
						<title>Virginia Base Map Program Imagery and Hydrology</title>
						<geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
						<pubinfo>
							<pubplace>Richmond, VA</pubplace>
						</pubinfo>
					</citeinfo>
				</srccite>
				<srccitea>VBMP 2006/07</srccitea>
				<srccontr>Imagery (2007) serves as a background in the map portfolio. Imagery is used to update land use and structure data as well as to remotely code areas not previously surveyed in the field.  The VBMP shoreline was also used and adjusted using the imagery where needed. This shoreline was used in the following counties: City of Chesapeake, City of Portsmouth, King George, New Kent, Newport News, and Mathews.</srccontr>
			</srcinfo>
			<srcinfo>
				<srccite>
					<citeinfo>
						<origin>Commonwealth of Virginia, through Virginia Geographic Network Division of its Department of Technology Planning (VGIN)</origin>
						<pubdate>2009, 2011</pubdate>
						<title>Virginia Base Mapping Program (VBMP)</title>
						<pubinfo>
							<pubplace>Richmond, VA</pubplace>
						</pubinfo>
					</citeinfo>
				</srccite>
				<srccitea>VBMP 2009, 2011</srccitea>
				<srccontr>Imagery (2009, 2011) serves as a background in the map portfolio. Used to accurately position land use and land cover data. Provided a new digital shoreline coverage that serves as the base shoreline for shoreline conditions. Used in the following counties: City of Virginia Beach, Henrico, Northampton, City of Suffolk, City of Poquoson, Charles City County, and York County.</srccontr>
			</srcinfo>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Data was collected by a three-person field crew (1989-2001) or a two-person field crew (2002 to present). From 2002 to 2012 a two-person crew consisted of one person collecting land use and bank condition data and one boat operator also collecting shoreline features using two hand-held Trimble GeoExplorers GPS Units, while navigating along the shoreline. A data dictionary designed for the inventory was installed on each GPS Unit. One data collector records natural features including land use, bank height, presence of marsh or beach, and shoreline stability. A second person collects data on the hardened structures: riprap, bulkheads, docks, boatramps, etc. Point features (docks, boathouses, ramps) were surveyed with a six second observation recorded at 1 reading/second. Linear features were surveyed kinematically at a rate of one observation every 3 seconds.  Begining in 2012 the two-person crew consists of a boat operator and one data surveyor. The boat operator navigates the boat to follow the shoreline geometry. The data surveyor uses a geo-referenced video camera. The Red Hen System provides hardware and software to collect geo-referenced video and photo data in the field. A standard video camera (sony ACC-HDV7) is interfaced with a GPS antennae via the Red Hen hardware device - VMS 300. VMS 300 converts GPS data into audio signals, which are sent to a video camera through its microphone input connector. As the video is recorded, GPS data are transmitted once per second to the video camera by VMS 300. Each GPS location is linked with a time code on the video. Therefore, the survey is a set of videos containing geographically referenced shoreline data.</procdesc>
				<procdate>1998 - present</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Data from the GPS units were postprocessed using Trimble Pathfinder Office software. Postprocessing included differential correction using CORS (Continuous Operating Reference Stations) data. Corrected data are converted to shape files for further processing in the GIS environment.</procdesc>
				<procdate>1998 - 2012</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>In the ArcMap environment, boat-track arcs and points were manually shifted to the base shoreline. Arcs were split and moved to locations on the shoreline perpendicular to the original locations on the boat-track. Points were also moved to locations on the shoreline perpendicular to the original locations on the boat-track.  Shoreline arc segments and points were coded, and the shapefiles were visually checked for attribute accuracy between coded shoreline and boat-track data.</procdesc>
				<procdate>1998 - present</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>The shoreline for Northampton was extracted from the VGIN LiDar derived, hydro flattened DEM for the Eastern Shore using the ArcMap contour tool. Bank height was generated from the VBMP. The 0, 5, 10 and 30 foot contours were derived from the VBMP Eastern Shore hydrologically correct DEM based on the 2010 LiDar survey, using the raster surface contour tool. It was decided that the bank would be within 10 meters of the 0 contour except on some beaches where the bank was visually further away. 10 meter buffers were created for the 5, 10 and 30 foot contours. Each of these buffers was run with the 0 contour in the intersect tool to make files showing where the contours were within 10 meters of the 0. In no case did the 30 foot contour intersect 0. The 3 files for 0, 5, and 10 were run in the identity tool to make the final file showing bank height feature attributes of 0-5, 5-10, and 10-30. This was merged with the land use data and became an attribute in the shapefile.</procdesc>
				<procdate>2011</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>For Henrico, and parts of Virginia Beach (Broad Bay and Rudy Inlet) data were logged using a geo-referenced video camera.</procdesc>
				<procdate>2012</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>For tributaries surveyed in the field using GPS referenced videography, the proprietary software associated with the Red Hen System is used for post processing: Pixpoint and GeoVideo for GIS. The PixPoint software package is used to generate a point shapefile containing points representing locations of geo-referenced still photos taken during the survey. GeoVideo software package is an ArcGIS extension. It is a desktop mapping application that brings the geo-referenced video directly into the ArcGIS environment. This software enables users to digitally map videos using GPS coordinates. After the videos are downloaded to the computer, the GeoVideo software is used to generate a point shapefile which is geotagged to the precise track of the video survey. This shapefile is a representation of the survey track. Along with the video link, it enables GIS personnel to code the shoreline conditions in ArcMap based on what is viewed in the video.</procdesc>
				<procdate>2012 - present</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Land use, point structure, and linear structure locations were digitally checked and repositioned if necessary with imagery displayed in the background. Coding takes place in the ArcMap environment using coding, heads-up digitizing, and photo-interpretation techniques. Areas inaccessible by boat due to low tide were coded based on features observed on the imagery. The "remote" coded areas were given the item REMOTE = "yes" to distinquish them from GPS collected data. Background image quality depends upon imagery available the year inventory was published. Begining in 2011/2012 recent high resolution color infra-red and natural color imagery (2009 and 2011) with a resolution of 1 meter or better is used along with Bing oblique imagery to identify and code the shoreline for shoreline attributes.</procdesc>
				<procdate>1998 - present</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Begining in 2012 marsh data is being collected separately and is no longer part of the shoreline inventory "lubc" shapefile. Marsh data (including phragmites information) will be in served in the updated Tidal Marsh Inventory (TMI): http://ccrm.vims.edu/gis_data_maps/static_maps/gis/tmi_updated.html</procdesc>
				<procdate>2012 - present</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>County inventories were merged together.</procdesc>
				<procdate>2009 - present</procdate>
			</procstep>
		</lineage>
	</dataqual>
	<eainfo>
		<detailed Name="va_astru_2013">
			<enttyp>
				<enttypl Sync="TRUE">va_astru_2013</enttypl>
				<enttypt Sync="TRUE">Feature Class</enttypt><enttypc Sync="TRUE">27043</enttypc></enttyp>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>FID</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
				<attalias Sync="TRUE">FID</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">OID</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">4</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
				<attalias Sync="TRUE">Shape</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Geometry</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">0</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>GPS_DATE</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Date of data capture</attrdef>
				<attalias Sync="TRUE">GPS_Date</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Date</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">8</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>REMOTE</attrlabl>
				<attrdomv>
					<edom>
						<edomv>yes</edomv>
						<edomvd>Data coded in the lab using background imagery</edomvd>
					</edom>
				</attrdomv>
				<attalias Sync="TRUE">REMOTE</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">10</attwidth></attr>
			<attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">PNTSTRUC</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">PNTSTRUC</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">30</attwidth><attrdef>outfalls and access structures: boathouse, dilapidated pier, pier, private boat ramp, and public boat ramp</attrdef><attrdomv><edom><edomv>Boathouse</edomv></edom><edom><edomv>Dilapidated Dock</edomv></edom><edom><edomv>Dock</edomv><edomvd>pier</edomvd></edom><edom><edomv>Outfall</edomv></edom><edom><edomv>Point of Interest</edomv></edom><edom><edomv>Private Ramp</edomv></edom><edom><edomv>Public Ramp</edomv></edom><edom><edomv>Ramp</edomv><edomvd>boat ramp. from an inventory prior to distinguishing between public and private ramps</edomvd></edom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">POINT_OF_I</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">POINT_OF_I</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">20</attwidth><attrdomv/><attrdef>point of interest. Counties inventoried between 1998 and 2002 may contain data in this field.</attrdef></attr><attr>
				<attrlabl>COUNTY</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>county or waterbody inventoried</attrdef>
				<attalias Sync="TRUE">COUNTY</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">25</attwidth><attrdomv/></attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>SURVEYED</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>year data collected</attrdef>
				<attalias Sync="TRUE">SURVEYED</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">50</attwidth><attrdomv/></attr>
			<attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">Field_Date</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">Field_Date</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Date</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">8</attwidth><attrdef>Date of field survey</attrdef></attr><attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">INVENTORY</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">INVENTORY</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">150</attwidth><attrdef>Year of inventory or year of  update using imagery</attrdef></attr></detailed>
		<overview>
			<eaover>Two other shapefiles combine with _lubc to complete the Shoreline Inventory. The complete set includes _lubc, _astru, and _sstru. Attributes in the _lubc file include: FEATURE or land use may contain the following values: agriculture, bare, commercial, educational/school, family dwelling, forest, grass, industrial, military, multifamily dwelling, paved, residential, scrub-shrub, and timbered; HEIGHT is the bank height with 0 - 5 feet, 5 - 10 feet, and 10 - 30 feet, and &gt;30; EROSION or bank erosion can have the values: low, high, undercut, erosional, erosional/undercut, stable, stable/undercut, transitional, or transition/undercut; MARSH values may be yes, no, yes(erosion), yes(no_erosion), embayed, extensive, and fringe &lt;5, 5-10, 10-15 and &gt;15; Beach values are the presence or absence of beach where "yes" indicates a beach and "no" or a null value indicates no beach;   Cover (bank cover) is defined as bare, partial, or total;  Tree Fringe is coded as 'Yes" for the presence of a tree buffer along the shoreline; Canopy overhang is "yes" if the tree fringe overhangs the shoreline; and REMOTE refers to how the data was gathered: a blank value indicates the data was collected with the GPS unit, a "y" indicates that the shoreline attributes where determined from imagery.  Phragmites australis is coded as 'yes' where its presence is noted.   Attributes in the _astru (access structure shapefile) are: PNTSTRUC contains access structures such as boathouse, dock, dilapidated dock, outfall, and public or private ramp; and REMOTE. Attributes found in the _sstru shapefile are: STRUCTURE (erosion control)with values such as breakwater, bulkhead, debris, dilapidated bulkhead, groinfield, jetty, marina, marsh toe revetment, military wharf, miscellaneous, riprap, seawall, shipyard, unconventional, and wharf; and REMOTE.</eaover>
		</overview>
	</eainfo>
	<metainfo>
		<metc>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntper>Tami Rudnicky</cntper>
					<cntorg>Virginia Institute of Marine Science (VIMS)</cntorg>
				</cntperp>
				<cntpos>GIS Programmer/Analyst</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>P.O. Box 1346</addrtype>
					<address>Greate Road</address>
					<city>Gloucester Point</city>
					<state>Virginia</state>
					<postal>23062</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>804-684-7181</cntvoice>
				<cntfax>804-684-7179</cntfax>
				<cntemail>tamia@vims.edu</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</metc>
		<langmeta Sync="TRUE">en</langmeta><metstdn Sync="TRUE">FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn><metstdv Sync="TRUE">FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv><mettc Sync="TRUE">local time</mettc><metd Sync="TRUE">20131011</metd><metextns><onlink Sync="TRUE">http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html</onlink><metprof Sync="TRUE">ESRI Metadata Profile</metprof></metextns></metainfo>
	<Esri><CreaDate>20131011</CreaDate><CreaTime>14384000</CreaTime><SyncOnce>FALSE</SyncOnce><SyncDate>20131011</SyncDate><SyncTime>15463500</SyncTime><ModDate>20131011</ModDate><ModTime>15463500</ModTime><DataProperties><itemProps><itemName Sync="TRUE">va_astru_2013</itemName><imsContentType Sync="TRUE">002</imsContentType><itemSize Sync="TRUE">0.722</itemSize><itemLocation><linkage Sync="TRUE">file://\\139.70.26.251\ccrm\cci\Shoreline_Inventories\Completed_Inventories\Virginia_Shoreline_Inventories\va_all_inv\Most_Recent_Combined_Virginia_Inventory\va_astru_2013</linkage><protocol Sync="TRUE">Local Area Network</protocol></itemLocation><nativeExtBox><westBL Sync="TRUE">286401.712300</westBL><eastBL Sync="TRUE">470584.893143</eastBL><southBL Sync="TRUE">4045425.983700</southBL><northBL Sync="TRUE">4300252.919623</northBL><exTypeCode Sync="TRUE">1</exTypeCode></nativeExtBox></itemProps><coordRef><type Sync="TRUE">Projected</type><geogcsn Sync="TRUE">GCS_North_American_1983</geogcsn><csUnits Sync="TRUE">Linear Unit: Meter (1.000000)</csUnits><projcsn Sync="TRUE">NAD_1983_UTM_Zone_18N</projcsn><peXml Sync="TRUE">&lt;ProjectedCoordinateSystem xsi:type='typens:ProjectedCoordinateSystem' xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance' xmlns:xs='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema' xmlns:typens='http://www.esri.com/schemas/ArcGIS/10.0'&gt;&lt;WKT&gt;PROJCS[&amp;quot;NAD_1983_UTM_Zone_18N&amp;quot;,GEOGCS[&amp;quot;GCS_North_American_1983&amp;quot;,DATUM[&amp;quot;D_North_American_1983&amp;quot;,SPHEROID[&amp;quot;GRS_1980&amp;quot;,6378137.0,298.257222101]],PRIMEM[&amp;quot;Greenwich&amp;quot;,0.0],UNIT[&amp;quot;Degree&amp;quot;,0.0174532925199433]],PROJECTION[&amp;quot;Transverse_Mercator&amp;quot;],PARAMETER[&amp;quot;False_Easting&amp;quot;,500000.0],PARAMETER[&amp;quot;False_Northing&amp;quot;,0.0],PARAMETER[&amp;quot;Central_Meridian&amp;quot;,-75.0],PARAMETER[&amp;quot;Scale_Factor&amp;quot;,0.9996],PARAMETER[&amp;quot;Latitude_Of_Origin&amp;quot;,0.0],UNIT[&amp;quot;Meter&amp;quot;,1.0],AUTHORITY[&amp;quot;EPSG&amp;quot;,26918]]&lt;/WKT&gt;&lt;XOrigin&gt;-5120900&lt;/XOrigin&gt;&lt;YOrigin&gt;-9998100&lt;/YOrigin&gt;&lt;XYScale&gt;450445547.3910538&lt;/XYScale&gt;&lt;ZOrigin&gt;-100000&lt;/ZOrigin&gt;&lt;ZScale&gt;10000&lt;/ZScale&gt;&lt;MOrigin&gt;-100000&lt;/MOrigin&gt;&lt;MScale&gt;10000&lt;/MScale&gt;&lt;XYTolerance&gt;0.001&lt;/XYTolerance&gt;&lt;ZTolerance&gt;0.001&lt;/ZTolerance&gt;&lt;MTolerance&gt;0.001&lt;/MTolerance&gt;&lt;HighPrecision&gt;true&lt;/HighPrecision&gt;&lt;WKID&gt;26918&lt;/WKID&gt;&lt;/ProjectedCoordinateSystem&gt;</peXml></coordRef><lineage><Process ToolSource="C:\Program Files\ArcGIS\Desktop10.0\ArcToolbox\Toolboxes\Analysis Tools.tbx\Select" Date="20131010" Time="145259">Select va_astru_2012_Oct2012 N:\cci\Shoreline_Inventories\Completed_Inventories\Virginia_Shoreline_Inventories\va_all_inv\shapefiles\va_astru_2013.shp #</Process><Process ToolSource="C:\Program Files\ArcGIS\Desktop10.0\ArcToolbox\Toolboxes\Data Management Tools.tbx\CalculateField" Date="20131010" Time="152146">CalculateField va_astru_2013 Field_Date [GPS_Date] VB #</Process><Process ToolSource="C:\Program Files\ArcGIS\Desktop10.0\ArcToolbox\Toolboxes\Data Management Tools.tbx\CalculateField" Date="20131010" Time="153017">CalculateField va_astru_2013 INVENTORY [SURVEYED] VB #</Process><Process ToolSource="C:\Program Files\ArcGIS\Desktop10.0\ArcToolbox\Toolboxes\Data Management Tools.tbx\Append" Date="20131010" Time="155305">Append CharlesCity_astru va_astru_2013 NO_TEST "GPS_Date "GPS_Date" true true false 8 Date 0 0 ,First,#;REMOTE "REMOTE" true false false 10 Text 0 0 ,First,#,C:\myworkspace\shlinv_working\CharlesCity_astru.shp,REMOTE,-1,-1;PNTSTRUC "PNTSTRUC" true false false 30 Text 0 0 ,First,#,C:\myworkspace\shlinv_working\CharlesCity_astru.shp,PNTSTRUC,-1,-1;POINT_OF_I "POINT_OF_I" true false false 20 Text 0 0 ,First,#;COUNTY "COUNTY" true false false 25 Text 0 0 ,First,#,C:\myworkspace\shlinv_working\CharlesCity_astru.shp,COUNTY,-1,-1;SURVEYED "SURVEYED" true false false 50 Text 0 0 ,First,#;Field_Date "Field_Date" true true false 8 Date 0 0 ,First,#,C:\myworkspace\shlinv_working\CharlesCity_astru.shp,Field_Date,-1,-1;INVENTORY "INVENTORY" true false false 150 Text 0 0 ,First,#,C:\myworkspace\shlinv_working\CharlesCity_astru.shp,INVENTORY,-1,-1" #</Process><Process ToolSource="C:\Program Files\ArcGIS\Desktop10.0\ArcToolbox\Toolboxes\Data Management Tools.tbx\Append" Date="20131010" Time="155355">Append poq_astru_2013 va_astru_2013 NO_TEST "GPS_Date "GPS_Date" true true false 8 Date 0 0 ,First,#;REMOTE "REMOTE" true false false 10 Text 0 0 ,First,#;PNTSTRUC "PNTSTRUC" true false false 30 Text 0 0 ,First,#,C:\myworkspace\shlinv_working\poq_astru_2013.shp,PNTSTRUC,-1,-1;POINT_OF_I "POINT_OF_I" true false false 20 Text 0 0 ,First,#;COUNTY "COUNTY" true false false 25 Text 0 0 ,First,#,C:\myworkspace\shlinv_working\poq_astru_2013.shp,COUNTY,-1,-1;SURVEYED "SURVEYED" true false false 50 Text 0 0 ,First,#;Field_Date "Field_Date" true true false 8 Date 0 0 ,First,#;INVENTORY "INVENTORY" true false false 150 Text 0 0 ,First,#,C:\myworkspace\shlinv_working\poq_astru_2013.shp,INVENTORY,-1,-1" #</Process><Process ToolSource="C:\Program Files\ArcGIS\Desktop10.0\ArcToolbox\Toolboxes\Data Management Tools.tbx\Append" Date="20131010" Time="155552">Append Suffolk_astru va_astru_2013 NO_TEST "GPS_Date "GPS_Date" true true false 8 Date 0 0 ,First,#;REMOTE "REMOTE" true false false 10 Text 0 0 ,First,#,C:\myworkspace\shlinv_working\Suffolk_astru.shp,REMOTE,-1,-1;PNTSTRUC "PNTSTRUC" true false false 30 Text 0 0 ,First,#,C:\myworkspace\shlinv_working\Suffolk_astru.shp,PNTSTRUC,-1,-1;POINT_OF_I "POINT_OF_I" true false false 20 Text 0 0 ,First,#;COUNTY "COUNTY" true false false 25 Text 0 0 ,First,#,C:\myworkspace\shlinv_working\Suffolk_astru.shp,COUNTY,-1,-1;SURVEYED "SURVEYED" true false false 50 Text 0 0 ,First,#;Field_Date "Field_Date" true true false 8 Date 0 0 ,First,#,C:\myworkspace\shlinv_working\Suffolk_astru.shp,Field_Date,-1,-1;INVENTORY "INVENTORY" true false false 150 Text 0 0 ,First,#,C:\myworkspace\shlinv_working\Suffolk_astru.shp,INVENTORY,-1,-1" #</Process><Process ToolSource="C:\Program Files\ArcGIS\Desktop10.0\ArcToolbox\Toolboxes\Data Management Tools.tbx\Append" Date="20131010" Time="155631">Append yorkco_astru_13 va_astru_2013 NO_TEST "GPS_Date "GPS_Date" true true false 8 Date 0 0 ,First,#;REMOTE "REMOTE" true false false 10 Text 0 0 ,First,#;PNTSTRUC "PNTSTRUC" true false false 30 Text 0 0 ,First,#,C:\myworkspace\shlinv_working\yorkco_astru_13.shp,pntstruc,-1,-1;POINT_OF_I "POINT_OF_I" true false false 20 Text 0 0 ,First,#;COUNTY "COUNTY" true false false 25 Text 0 0 ,First,#,C:\myworkspace\shlinv_working\yorkco_astru_13.shp,COUNTY,-1,-1;SURVEYED "SURVEYED" true false false 50 Text 0 0 ,First,#;Field_Date "Field_Date" true true false 8 Date 0 0 ,First,#;INVENTORY "INVENTORY" true false false 150 Text 0 0 ,First,#,C:\myworkspace\shlinv_working\yorkco_astru_13.shp,INVENTORY,-1,-1" #</Process><Process ToolSource="C:\Program Files\ArcGIS\Desktop10.0\ArcToolbox\Toolboxes\Data Management Tools.tbx\CalculateField" Date="20131010" Time="160749">CalculateField va_astru_2013 PNTSTRUC "Dilapidated Dock" VB #</Process><Process ToolSource="C:\Program Files\ArcGIS\Desktop10.0\ArcToolbox\Toolboxes\Data Management Tools.tbx\CalculateField" Date="20131010" Time="160820">CalculateField va_astru_2013 PNTSTRUC "Dock" VB #</Process><Process ToolSource="C:\Program Files\ArcGIS\Desktop10.0\ArcToolbox\Toolboxes\Data Management Tools.tbx\CalculateField" Date="20131010" Time="160857">CalculateField va_astru_2013 PNTSTRUC "Private Ramp" VB #</Process><Process ToolSource="C:\Program Files\ArcGIS\Desktop10.0\ArcToolbox\Toolboxes\Data Management Tools.tbx\CalculateField" Date="20131010" Time="160919">CalculateField va_astru_2013 PNTSTRUC "Public Ramp" VB #</Process><Process ToolSource="C:\Program Files\ArcGIS\Desktop10.0\ArcToolbox\Toolboxes\Data Management Tools.tbx\CalculateField" Date="20131010" Time="160943">CalculateField va_astru_2013 PNTSTRUC "Outfall" VB #</Process><Process ToolSource="C:\Program Files\ArcGIS\Desktop10.0\ArcToolbox\Toolboxes\Data Management Tools.tbx\CalculateField" Date="20131010" Time="161013">CalculateField va_astru_2013 PNTSTRUC "Boathouse" VB #</Process><Process ToolSource="C:\Program Files\ArcGIS\Desktop10.0\ArcToolbox\Toolboxes\Data Management Tools.tbx\CalculateField" Date="20131010" Time="161610">CalculateField va_astru_2013 INVENTORY "Inventory updated in 2013 using VBMP 2011 imagery / Bing high resolution oblique imagery" VB #</Process></lineage><copyHistory><copy source="C:\myworkspace\shlinv_working\va_astru_2013" dest="\\139.70.26.251\ccrm\cci\Shoreline_Inventories\Completed_Inventories\Virginia_Shoreline_Inventories\va_all_inv\Most_Recent_Combined_Virginia_Inventory\va_astru_2013" date="20131011" time="14384000"></copy></copyHistory></DataProperties><ArcGISstyle>FGDC CSDGM Metadata</ArcGISstyle></Esri><dataIdInfo><envirDesc Sync="TRUE">Microsoft Windows Vista Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.1.3500</envirDesc><dataLang><languageCode Sync="TRUE" value="en"></languageCode><countryCode value="US" Sync="TRUE"></countryCode></dataLang><idCitation><resTitle Sync="TRUE">va_astru_2013</resTitle><presForm><PresFormCd Sync="TRUE" value="005"></PresFormCd></presForm></idCitation><spatRpType><SpatRepTypCd Sync="TRUE" value="001"></SpatRepTypCd></spatRpType><dataExt><geoEle><GeoBndBox esriExtentType="native"><westBL Sync="TRUE">286401.7123</westBL><eastBL Sync="TRUE">470584.893143</eastBL><northBL Sync="TRUE">4300252.919623</northBL><southBL Sync="TRUE">4045425.9837</southBL><exTypeCode Sync="TRUE">1</exTypeCode></GeoBndBox></geoEle></dataExt><geoBox esriExtentType="decdegrees"><westBL Sync="TRUE">-77.460521</westBL><eastBL Sync="TRUE">-75.328685</eastBL><northBL Sync="TRUE">38.850606</northBL><southBL Sync="TRUE">36.53038</southBL><exTypeCode Sync="TRUE">1</exTypeCode></geoBox><dataExt><geoEle><GeoBndBox esriExtentType="search"><exTypeCode Sync="TRUE">1</exTypeCode><westBL Sync="TRUE">-77.460521</westBL><eastBL Sync="TRUE">-75.328685</eastBL><northBL Sync="TRUE">38.850606</northBL><southBL Sync="TRUE">36.530380</southBL></GeoBndBox></geoEle></dataExt></dataIdInfo><mdLang><languageCode Sync="TRUE" value="en"></languageCode><countryCode value="US" Sync="TRUE"></countryCode></mdLang><mdStanName Sync="TRUE">ISO 19115 Geographic Information - Metadata</mdStanName><mdStanVer Sync="TRUE">DIS_ESRI1.0</mdStanVer><mdChar><CharSetCd Sync="TRUE" value="004"></CharSetCd></mdChar><mdHrLv><ScopeCd Sync="TRUE" value="005"></ScopeCd></mdHrLv><mdHrLvName Sync="TRUE">dataset</mdHrLvName><distinfo><resdesc Sync="TRUE">Downloadable Data</resdesc><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><transize Sync="TRUE">0.722</transize><dssize Sync="TRUE">0.722</dssize></digtinfo></digform></stdorder></distinfo><distInfo><distributor><distorTran><onLineSrc><orDesc Sync="TRUE">002</orDesc><linkage Sync="TRUE">file://\\139.70.26.251\ccrm\cci\Shoreline_Inventories\Completed_Inventories\Virginia_Shoreline_Inventories\va_all_inv\Most_Recent_Combined_Virginia_Inventory\va_astru_2013.shp</linkage><protocol Sync="TRUE">Local Area Network</protocol></onLineSrc><transSize Sync="TRUE">0.722</transSize></distorTran><distorFormat><formatName Sync="TRUE">Shapefile</formatName></distorFormat></distributor><distFormat><formatName Sync="TRUE">Shapefile</formatName></distFormat><distTranOps><transSize Sync="TRUE">0.722</transSize></distTranOps></distInfo><spdoinfo><direct Sync="TRUE">Vector</direct><ptvctinf><esriterm Name="va_astru_2013"><efeatyp Sync="TRUE">Simple</efeatyp><efeageom code="1" Sync="TRUE">Point</efeageom><esritopo Sync="TRUE">FALSE</esritopo><efeacnt Sync="TRUE">27043</efeacnt><spindex Sync="TRUE">TRUE</spindex><linrefer Sync="TRUE">FALSE</linrefer></esriterm><sdtsterm Name="va_astru_2013"><sdtstype Sync="TRUE">Entity point</sdtstype><ptvctcnt Sync="TRUE">27043</ptvctcnt></sdtsterm></ptvctinf></spdoinfo><spref><horizsys><cordsysn><geogcsn Sync="TRUE">GCS_North_American_1983</geogcsn><projcsn Sync="TRUE">NAD_1983_UTM_Zone_18N</projcsn></cordsysn><planar><planci><plance Sync="TRUE">coordinate pair</plance><plandu Sync="TRUE">meters</plandu><coordrep><absres Sync="TRUE">0.000000</absres><ordres Sync="TRUE">0.000000</ordres></coordrep></planci><gridsys><gridsysn Sync="TRUE">Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone Sync="TRUE">18</utmzone><transmer><sfctrmer Sync="TRUE">0.999600</sfctrmer><longcm Sync="TRUE">-75.000000</longcm><latprjo Sync="TRUE">0.000000</latprjo><feast Sync="TRUE">500000.000000</feast><fnorth Sync="TRUE">0.000000</fnorth></transmer></utm></gridsys></planar><geodetic><horizdn Sync="TRUE">North American Datum of 1983</horizdn><ellips Sync="TRUE">Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips><semiaxis Sync="TRUE">6378137.000000</semiaxis><denflat Sync="TRUE">298.257222</denflat></geodetic></horizsys></spref><refSysInfo><RefSystem><refSysID><identCode Sync="TRUE" value="26918">NAD_1983_UTM_Zone_18N</identCode><idCodeSpace Sync="TRUE">EPSG</idCodeSpace><idVersion Sync="TRUE">7.4.1</idVersion></refSysID></RefSystem></refSysInfo><spatRepInfo><VectSpatRep><topLvl><TopoLevCd value="001" Sync="TRUE"></TopoLevCd></topLvl><geometObjs Name="va_astru_2013"><geoObjTyp><GeoObjTypCd Sync="TRUE" value="004"></GeoObjTypCd></geoObjTyp><geoObjCnt Sync="TRUE">27043</geoObjCnt></geometObjs></VectSpatRep></spatRepInfo><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20131011</mdDateSt></metadata>
