<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata>
	<idinfo>
		<citation>
			<citeinfo>
				<origin>Comprehensive Coastal Inventory, Virginia Institute of Marine Science</origin>
				<pubdate>2009</pubdate>
				<title Sync="TRUE">math08_sstru</title>
				<geoform Sync="TRUE">vector digital data</geoform>
				<pubinfo>
					<pubplace>Gloucester Point, Virginia</pubplace>
					<publish>Virginia Institute of Marine Science</publish>
				</pubinfo>
				<onlink>http://ccrm.vims.edu/gis_data_maps/shoreline_inventories/index.html</onlink>
				<ftname Sync="TRUE">math08_sstru</ftname></citeinfo>
		</citation>
		<descript>
			<abstract>Shoreline Situation Reports (SSR) were first generated by VIMS in the 1970's to report the condition and status of the shore lands.  The SSR series were published in hardcopy on a county by county basis for each Tidewater Virginia localities.  The reports were intended to assist planners, managers, and regulators in decisions pertaining to management of coastal areas and natural resources therein.  This Shoreline Inventory report continues a process which updates and expands the earlier reports.  Data collected reports conditions surveyed in the immediate riparian zone, the bank, and along the shoreline.</abstract>
			<purpose>To inventory Virginia's tidal shoreline conditions.</purpose>
			<supplinf>There are three shapefiles that are part of the 2008 Mathews County Shoreline Inventory database: math08_lubc, math08_astru, math08_sstru. Math08_lubc (land use and bank cover for Mathews  County) is a linear shapefile containing data about land use, bank height, bank cover, Phragmites australis, tree fringe, canopy overhang, erosion, marsh, and beach status along the shoreline. Math08_sstru (Mathews County shoreline structures) is a linear shapefile delineating hard structures in place at the shoreline (bulkhead, riprap, breakwater, debris, dilapidated bulkhead, jetty, marina, marsh toe revetment, unconventional, wharf, groin fields). Math08_astru (Mathews County structures) is a point shapefile with locations of docks, ramps, dilapidated docks, outfalls and boathouses. The attributes of these three shapefiles are explained in the Entity and Attribute Information section below.</supplinf>
			<langdata Sync="TRUE">en</langdata></descript>
		<timeperd>
			<timeinfo>
				<rngdates>
					<begdate>06/06/2008</begdate>
					<enddate>06/26/2008</enddate>
				</rngdates>
			</timeinfo>
			<current>ground condition at time of survey</current>
		</timeperd>
		<status>
			<progress>Complete</progress>
			<update>Unknown</update>
		</status>
		<keywords>
			<theme>
				<themekt>none</themekt>
				<themekey>Shoreline conditions</themekey>
				<themekey>Shoreline structures</themekey>
				<themekey>Riparian Land use</themekey>
				<themekey>Shoreline Inventory</themekey>
			</theme>
			<place>
				<placekt>none</placekt>
				<placekey>Virginia</placekey>
				<placekey>Chesapeake Bay</placekey>
				<placekey>Mobjack Bay</placekey>
				<placekey>Piankatank River</placekey>
				<placekey>Mathews County</placekey>
			</place>
		</keywords>
		<accconst>none</accconst>
		<useconst>These data should not be used for jurisdictional permit determinations beyond providing general shoreline condition or status information.  These data have not been surveyed to property boundaries.</useconst>
		<ptcontac>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntper>Marcia Berman</cntper>
					<cntorg>Virginia Institute of Marine Science (VIMS)</cntorg>
				</cntperp>
				<cntpos>Director of Comprehensive Coastal Inventory Program (CCI)</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>P.O. Box 1346</addrtype>
					<address>Greate Road</address>
					<city>Gloucester Point</city>
					<state>Virginia</state>
					<postal>23062</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>804-684-7188</cntvoice>
				<cntfax>804-684-7179</cntfax>
				<cntemail>marcia@vims.edu</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</ptcontac>
		<native Sync="TRUE">Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 3; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.0.1770</native><spdom><bounding><westbc Sync="TRUE">-76.449636</westbc><eastbc Sync="TRUE">-76.245607</eastbc><northbc Sync="TRUE">37.531214</northbc><southbc Sync="TRUE">37.298896</southbc></bounding><lboundng><leftbc Sync="TRUE">371912.413394</leftbc><rightbc Sync="TRUE">389607.142071</rightbc><bottombc Sync="TRUE">4129009.781412</bottombc><topbc Sync="TRUE">4154537.626259</topbc></lboundng></spdom><natvform Sync="TRUE">Shapefile</natvform></idinfo>
	<dataqual>
		<attracc>
			<attraccr>The attributes were compared to original GPS data logs for accuracy.  Errors were corrected where noted.</attraccr>
		</attracc>
		<logic>Chain-node topology present.  Linear coverages were built for lines and point coverages were built for points.</logic>
		<complete>All shoreline of Mathews County that has a minimum depth of 2 feet at mean low water was surveyed.  Some shorelines are coded remotely if access was restricted due to depth.</complete>
		<posacc>
			<horizpa>
				<horizpar>Shoreline structures were recorded with a GPS unit as the boat moved along the shoreline. Data was transferred from the GPS boat track to an existing digital shoreline coverage by projecting data to the shoreline at a 90 degree angle from the boat track. Rectified digital orthophoto quads were used as a background coverage to aid in data positioning. Dock and boathouse point data were aligned with docks on the images. Land use features were placed along the shore so changes in land use were coincident with changes illustrated in the imagery. Positional accuracy for data that has been corrected with imagery is  .3 meters (equivalent to image resolution). Data not visable on the imagery (bulkheads, riprap, etc.) has a positional accuracy of  11 meters. Accuracy was determined by comparing digitally processed data locations to onsite GPS ground surveys collected at random.</horizpar>
			</horizpa>
		</posacc>
		<lineage>
			<srcinfo>
				<srccite>
					<citeinfo>
						<origin>Commonwealth of Virginia, through Virginia Geographic Network Division of its Department of Technology Planning (VGIN)</origin>
						<pubdate>2006/2007</pubdate>
						<title>Virginia Base Map Program Imagery and Hydrology</title>
						<geoform>vector digital data</geoform>
					</citeinfo>
				</srccite>
				<srccontr>Imagery (2007) serves as a background in the map portfolio. Imagery is used to update land use and structure data as well as to remotely code areas not previously surveyed in the field.  The VBMP shoreline was also used and adjusted using the imagery where needed.</srccontr>
			</srcinfo>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Data was collected by a two-person field crew (one person collecting land use and bank condition data and one boat operator also collecting shoreline features) using two hand-held Trimble GeoExplorers GPS Units, while navigating along the shoreline. A data dictionary designed for the inventory was installed on each GPS Unit. One data collector records natural features including land use, bank height, presence of marsh or beach, and shoreline stability. A second person collects data on the hardened structures: riprap, bulkheads, docks, boatramps, etc. Point features (docks, boathouses, ramps) were surveyed with a six second observation recorded at 1 reading/second. Linear features were surveyed kinematically at a rate of one observation every 3 seconds.</procdesc>
				<procdate>2008</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Data from the GPS units were postprocessed on a PC with Trimble Pathfinder Office software. Postprocessing includes differential correction using base station data collected at the VIMS laboratory. Corrected data is converted to shapefiles for further processing.</procdesc>
				<procdate>2008</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>In the ArcMap environment, boat-track arcs were manually shifted to the base shoreline (VBMP). Arcs were split and moved to locations on the shoreline perpendicular to the original locations on the boat-track. Shoreline arc segments were coded, and the shapefiles were visually checked for attribute accuracy between coded shoreline and boat-track data.</procdesc>
				<procdate>2008</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>In ArcMap, boat-track points were manually shifted to the base shoreline (VBMP). Points were moved to locations on the shoreline perpendicular to the original locations on the boat-track. Points were coded and the access structure (astru) was visually checked for attribute accuracy between coded shoreline and boat-track data.</procdesc>
				<procdate>2008</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Land use, dock, and boathouse locations were digitally checked and repositioned if necessary with VBMP imagery displayed as a background coverage. This was done using ArcMap capabilities. Areas inaccessible by boat due to low tide were coded based on features observed on the imagery. The "remote" coded areas were given the item REMOTE = "yes" to distinquish them from GPS collected data.</procdesc>
				<procdate>2008</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>A portfolio containing twenty-three 1:12,000 scale plates was created for Mathews County. Each plate shows four maps: riparian land use, bank conditions, shoreline features, and natural buffers.   VBMP (2007) imagery is displayed in the background to provide users with additional information.</procdesc>
				<procdate>2008</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep><procdesc Sync="TRUE">Metadata imported.</procdesc><srcused Sync="TRUE">C:\DOCUME~1\sharon\LOCALS~1\Temp\xml194A.tmp</srcused><procdate Sync="TRUE">20090505</procdate><proctime Sync="TRUE">11592900</proctime></procstep></lineage>
	</dataqual>
	<eainfo>
		<detailed Name="math08_sstru">
			<enttyp>
				<enttypl Sync="TRUE">math08_sstru</enttypl>
				<enttypt Sync="TRUE">Feature Class</enttypt><enttypc Sync="TRUE">3540</enttypc></enttyp>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>FID</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<edom></edom>
				</attrdomv>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
				<attalias Sync="TRUE">FID</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">OID</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">4</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
				<attalias Sync="TRUE">Shape</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Geometry</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">0</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>LENGTH</attrlabl>
				<attalias Sync="TRUE">LENGTH</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Float</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">19</attwidth><atnumdec Sync="TRUE">11</atnumdec></attr>
			<attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">STRUCTURE</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">STRUCTURE</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">25</attwidth><attrdef>hardened conditions at the shoreline: breakwater, bulkhead, dilapidated bulkhead, debris, groinfield, jetty, marina, marsh toe revetment, riprap, unconventional, and wharf</attrdef></attr><attr>
				<attrlabl>remote</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>coded in the lab using background imagery</attrdef>
				<attalias Sync="TRUE">REMOTE</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">4</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>GPS_DATE</attrlabl>
				<attalias Sync="TRUE">GPS_DATE</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Date</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">8</attwidth></attr>
		</detailed>
		<overview>
			<eaover>Two other shapefiles combine with _lubc to complete the Mathews 2008 Shoreline Inventory. The complete set includes _lubc, _astru, and _sstru. Attributes in the _lubc file include: FEATURE or land use contains the following values: agriculture, commercial, forest, grass, paved, residential, scrub-shrub, and bare; HEIGHT is the bank height with 0 - 5 feet, 5 - 10 feet, and 10 - 30 feet, and &gt;30; EROSION or bank erosion can have the values: low or high or undercut; MARSH values are embayed, extensive, and fringe &lt;5, 5-10, 10-15 and &gt;15, and Beach values are the presence or absence of beach;   Cover is bank cover and defined as bare, partial, and total coverage;  Tree Fringe is coded as 'Yes" for the presence of a tree buffer along theshoreline, Canopy overhang is if the tree fringe overhangs the shoreline;   Cover is bank cover and defined as bare, partial, and total coverage; and REMOTE refers to how the data was gathered: a blank value indicates the data was collected with the GPS unit, a "y" indicates that the shoreline attributes where determined from the 2007 VBMP imagery.  Phragmites australis is coded as 'yes' where its presence is noted.   Attributes in the _astru (access structure shapefile) are: PNTSTRUC contains access structures such as boathouse, dock, dilapidated dock, outfall, and public or private ramp; and REMOTE. Attributes found in the _sstru shapefile are: STRUCTURE (erosion control)with values such as bulkhead, dilapidated bulkhead, groinfield,  marina, unconventional and riprap; and REMOTE.</eaover>
		</overview>
	</eainfo>
	<metainfo>
		<metc>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntper>Sharon Killeen</cntper>
					<cntorg>Virginia Institute of Marine Science  (VIMS)</cntorg>
				</cntperp>
				<cntpos>GIS Programmer</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>P.O. Box 1346</addrtype>
					<address>Greate Road</address>
					<city>Gloucester Point</city>
					<state>Virginia</state>
					<postal>23062</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>804-684-7534</cntvoice>
				<cntfax>804-684-7179</cntfax>
				<cntemail>sharon@vims.edu</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</metc>
		<metstdn Sync="TRUE">FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
		<metstdv Sync="TRUE">FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
		<mettc Sync="TRUE">local time</mettc>
		<langmeta Sync="TRUE">en</langmeta><metd Sync="TRUE">20090512</metd><metextns><onlink Sync="TRUE">http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html</onlink><metprof Sync="TRUE">ESRI Metadata Profile</metprof></metextns></metainfo>
	<Esri><MetaID>{CF5F7ECA-C104-40E0-B7DD-2445271471A3}</MetaID><CreaDate>20090505</CreaDate><CreaTime>11592900</CreaTime><SyncOnce>FALSE</SyncOnce><SyncDate>20090512</SyncDate><SyncTime>09074500</SyncTime><ModDate>20090512</ModDate><ModTime>09074500</ModTime></Esri><dataIdInfo><envirDesc Sync="TRUE">Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 3; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.0.1770</envirDesc><dataLang><languageCode Sync="TRUE" value="en"></languageCode></dataLang><idCitation><resTitle Sync="TRUE">math08_sstru</resTitle><presForm><PresFormCd Sync="TRUE" value="005"></PresFormCd></presForm></idCitation><spatRpType><SpatRepTypCd Sync="TRUE" value="001"></SpatRepTypCd></spatRpType><dataExt><geoEle><GeoBndBox esriExtentType="native"><westBL Sync="TRUE">371912.413394</westBL><eastBL Sync="TRUE">389607.142071</eastBL><northBL Sync="TRUE">4154537.626259</northBL><southBL Sync="TRUE">4129009.781412</southBL><exTypeCode Sync="TRUE">1</exTypeCode></GeoBndBox></geoEle></dataExt><geoBox esriExtentType="decdegrees"><westBL Sync="TRUE">-76.449636</westBL><eastBL Sync="TRUE">-76.245607</eastBL><northBL Sync="TRUE">37.531214</northBL><southBL Sync="TRUE">37.298896</southBL><exTypeCode Sync="TRUE">1</exTypeCode></geoBox></dataIdInfo><mdLang><languageCode Sync="TRUE" value="en"></languageCode></mdLang><mdStanName Sync="TRUE">ISO 19115 Geographic Information - Metadata</mdStanName><mdStanVer Sync="TRUE">DIS_ESRI1.0</mdStanVer><mdChar><CharSetCd Sync="TRUE" value="004"></CharSetCd></mdChar><mdHrLv><ScopeCd Sync="TRUE" value="005"></ScopeCd></mdHrLv><mdHrLvName Sync="TRUE">dataset</mdHrLvName><distinfo><resdesc Sync="TRUE">Downloadable Data</resdesc><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><transize Sync="TRUE">1.693</transize><dssize Sync="TRUE">1.693</dssize></digtinfo></digform></stdorder></distinfo><distInfo><distributor><distorTran><onLineSrc><orDesc Sync="TRUE">002</orDesc><linkage Sync="TRUE">file://\\139.70.26.250\ccrm\cci\portfolios\mathews_inv_2008\final_shapefiles\math08_sstru.shp</linkage><protocol Sync="TRUE">Local Area Network</protocol></onLineSrc><transSize Sync="TRUE">1.693</transSize></distorTran><distorFormat><formatName Sync="TRUE">Shapefile</formatName></distorFormat></distributor></distInfo><spdoinfo><direct Sync="TRUE">Vector</direct><ptvctinf><esriterm Name="math08_sstru"><efeatyp Sync="TRUE">Simple</efeatyp><efeageom Sync="TRUE">Polyline</efeageom><esritopo Sync="TRUE">FALSE</esritopo><efeacnt Sync="TRUE">3540</efeacnt><spindex Sync="TRUE">FALSE</spindex><linrefer Sync="TRUE">FALSE</linrefer></esriterm><sdtsterm Name="math08_sstru"><sdtstype Sync="TRUE">String</sdtstype><ptvctcnt Sync="TRUE">3540</ptvctcnt></sdtsterm></ptvctinf></spdoinfo><spref><horizsys><cordsysn><geogcsn Sync="TRUE">GCS_North_American_1983</geogcsn><projcsn Sync="TRUE">NAD_1983_UTM_Zone_18N</projcsn></cordsysn><planar><planci><plance Sync="TRUE">coordinate pair</plance><plandu Sync="TRUE">meters</plandu><coordrep><absres Sync="TRUE">0.000000</absres><ordres Sync="TRUE">0.000000</ordres></coordrep></planci><gridsys><gridsysn Sync="TRUE">Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone Sync="TRUE">18</utmzone><transmer><sfctrmer Sync="TRUE">0.999600</sfctrmer><longcm Sync="TRUE">-75.000000</longcm><latprjo Sync="TRUE">0.000000</latprjo><feast Sync="TRUE">500000.000000</feast><fnorth Sync="TRUE">0.000000</fnorth></transmer></utm></gridsys></planar><geodetic><horizdn Sync="TRUE">North American Datum of 1983</horizdn><ellips Sync="TRUE">Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips><semiaxis Sync="TRUE">6378137.000000</semiaxis><denflat Sync="TRUE">298.257222</denflat></geodetic></horizsys></spref><refSysInfo><RefSystem><refSysID><identCode Sync="TRUE">NAD_1983_UTM_Zone_18N</identCode></refSysID></RefSystem></refSysInfo><spatRepInfo><VectSpatRep><topLvl><TopoLevCd Sync="TRUE" value="001"></TopoLevCd></topLvl><geometObjs Name="math08_sstru"><geoObjTyp><GeoObjTypCd Sync="TRUE" value="001"></GeoObjTypCd></geoObjTyp><geoObjCnt Sync="TRUE">3540</geoObjCnt></geometObjs></VectSpatRep></spatRepInfo><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20090512</mdDateSt></metadata>
