











                 University of Nebraska - Lincoln
                 DigitalCommons@University of Nebraska - Lincoln


                 USGS Staff -- Published Research                                          US Geological Survey




                 1-1-2003

                 Birth of the Modern Chesapeake Bay Estuary

                 Between 7.4 and 8.2 Ka and Implications for Global

                 Sea-Level Rise



                 John F. Bratton
                 U.S. Geological Survey, Woods Hole Field Center, 384 Woods Hole Rd., Woods Hole, Massachusetts 02543-1598, USA

                 Steven M. Colman
                 U.S. Geological Survey, Woods Hole Field Center, 384 Woods Hole Rd., Woods Hole, Massachusetts 02543-1598, USA

                 E. Robert Thieler
                 U.S. Geological Survey, Woods Hole Field Center, 384 Woods Hole Rd., Woods Hole, Massachusetts 02543-1598, USA
                 Robert R. Seal II
                 U.S. Geological Survey, 954 National Center, 12201 Sunrise Valley Dr., Reston, Virginia

















                 Bratton, John F.; Colman, Steven M.; Thieler, E. Robert; and Seal II, Robert R., "Birth of the Modern Chesapeake Bay Estuary
                 Between 7.4 and 8.2 Ka and Implications for Global Sea-Level Rise" (2003). USGS Staff -- Published Research.  Paper 285.
                 http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/usgsstaffpub/285


                 This Article is brought to you for free and open access by the US Geological Survey at DigitalCommons@University of Nebraska - Lincoln. It has been
                 accepted for inclusion in USGS Staff -- Published Research by an authorized administrator of DigitalCommons@University of Nebraska - Lincoln.

 = Page 1 =


           Geo-Mar Lett (2003) 22: 188–197
           DOI 10.1007/s00367-002-0112-z                     This article is a U.S. government work, and is not subject to copyright in the United States.




                         Æ
           John F. Bratton Steven M. Colman
                          Æ
           E. Robert Thieler Robert R. Seal II
           Birth of the modern Chesapeake Bay estuary between 7.4
           and 8.2 ka and implications for global sea-level rise







           Received: 10 September 2001 /Accepted: 15 September 2002 / Published online: 8 November 2002
             Springer-Verlag 2002


           Abstract  Two major pulses of sea-level rise are thought  transition interval from rapid rise to slow rise, however,
           to have taken place since the last glacial maximum –  are not as well constrained as other parts of the Holo-
           meltwater pulses (mwp) 1A (12 cal ka) and 1B       cenerecord.Forexample,mostpeatunderlyingmodern
           (9.5 cal ka).Betweenmwp1Bandabout6 cal ka,many     salt marshes which are used as proxies for sea level
           ofthecomplexcoastalecosystemswhichringtheworld’s   postdate this time; older, submerged or buried peat is
           oceansbegantoform.Herewereportdataforrhenium,      commonly diﬃcult to ﬁnd, hard to sample, and hard to
           carbon isotopes, total organic carbon, andfossil oysters  distinguish from freshwater peat. Constraining the de-
           from Chesapeake Bay which span the transition from  tails of the prehistoric transition in the rate of sea-level
           freshtobrackishwaterconditionsinthebayinthemid-    rise has some urgency, however, because the near-still-
           Holocene. These data constrain sea-level change and  stand since about 6 cal ka may not be the ultimate
           resultingenvironmentalchangeinthebay.Theyindicate  highstandofthecurrentinterglacial;future,abruptrises
           that the transition was rapid, and that it was produced  appear entirely possible (Oppenheimer 1998).
           by(1)athirdpulseofrapideustaticsea-levelrise,or(2)   In this study we examine long sediment cores col-
           a geometry of the prehistoric Chesapeake Bay basin  lected from shallow and deep sites in the Chesapeake
           which predisposed it to a nonlinear response to a  Bay estuary which are expected to record the transition
           steadily rising sea level. Similar nonlinear changes in  intervalinsea-levelrise.Wecombinewell-datedproﬁles
           vulnerable coastal environments are likely to take place  of sediment geochemistry from these sites with bathy-
           in the future due to polar warming, regardless of the  metric, sedimentological, and faunal data. With these
           timing or rate of sea-level rise.                  data sets we reconstruct a continuous history which
                                                              spans the period of 9 to 6 cal ka and clearly shows the
                                                              transition from ﬂuvial fresh to consistently brackish
                                                              conditions – i.e., the birth of the modern Chesapeake
           Introduction                                       Bay estuary.

           Based on fossil corals (Lighty et al. 1982; Fairbanks
           1989) and the initiation of formation of modern deltas  Background
           (Stanley and Warne 1994) and other coastal features,
           suchassaltmarshesandbarrierislands,therapidrateof  Chesapeake Bay is the largest estuary in the United
           eustatic sea-level rise during the early to middle Holo-  States. It has a surface area of 11,100 km and is over
                                                                                                   2
           ceneappearstohaveslowedconsiderablyby6 cal ka,to   300 km long, with an average width of 20 km. Like
                            –1
           about 1.5 mm year . Details of sea level during the  other coastal-plain estuaries, Chesapeake Bay formed
                                                              during the later stages of retreat of the continental ice
                                                              sheets of the last glaciation. The ocean then ﬂooded the
                                                              paleo-river valley of the Susquehanna River and its
                                   Æ
           J.F. Bratton ( & ) S.M. Colman E.R. Thieler        tributaries which had been exposed during the glacial
                        Æ
           U.S. Geological Survey, Woods Hole Field Center,   lowstand (Colman and Mixon 1988; Colman et al.
           384 Woods Hole Rd., Woods Hole,
           Massachusetts 02543-1598, USA                      1990). The average depthof Chesapeake Bay is 8 m but
           E-mail: jbratton@usgs.gov                          an axial channel, a remnant of the old river valley, runs
           R.R. Seal II                                       down the center of the bay, reaching depths of 54 m
           U.S. Geological Survey, 954 National Center,       (Fig. 1). The work described here is part of a larger
           12201 Sunrise Valley Dr., Reston, Virginia 21092-0002, USA  sediment coring eﬀort begun in 1996 to complement

 = Page 2 =


                                                                                                            189








































































           Fig. 1  MapshowingChesapeakeBaybathymetryandlocationsof  earlier geophysical investigations of Quaternary sedi-
           sediment coring sites. Bathymetric contours are in feet (6, 12, 18,  mentation in the bay (Colman and Hobbs 1987, 1988;
           30,36,and60;1.8,3.7,5.5,9.1,11.0,and18.3 m,respectively);the  Colman and Halka 1989a, 1989b). Preliminary reports
           60-foot contour (>18.3 m) corresponds to the approximate
           boundary of the freshwater Chesapeake prior to 8.2 cal ka.  of coring results have included Kerhin et al. (1998),
           Bathymetric data are from NOAA. Data from coring sites 3 and  Cronin (2000), and Baucom et al. (2001).
           4 are not included in this discussion but the numbering system is  The focus of the investigation of long sediment cores
           maintained for consistency with Colman et al. (2002)  presented here (Fig. 2) is geochemical and paleo-envi-
                                                              ronmental aspects of the transition interval from ﬂuvial

 = Page 3 =


           190
           Fig. 2  Core lithologies and ra-
           diocarbon sample depths and
           ages (cal a . .)
                   B P














































           to estuarine conditions in Chesapeake Bay. Typical es-  of the sediments are described in more detail by Cronin
           tuarine sediments recovered in cores consisted of dark  (2000) and Baucom et al. (2001); basic core lithologies
           gray to black silt and clay with varying amounts of ﬁne  areshownonFig. 2.Coreswerecollectedinﬁberglassor
           to medium sand and shells, especially shells of the  PVC liners and they were cut into 1.5-m lengths and
           opportunistic bivalve  Mulinia lateralis , as well as  Cras-  capped immediately after retrieval of the corer. Refrig-
           sostrea virginica  and  Mercenaria mercenaria . The shal-  erated cores were split lengthwise and bulk-sampled in
           low-watercore(site 5)wasgenerallycoarsergrainedand  either 2- or 3-cm slices. Subsamples for geochemical
           more bioturbated than the cores from the deep axial  analysiswerecollectedfromdiscretedepthsimmediately
           channel (sites 1 and 6).                           priortobulksampling.Spacingofanalyzedsampleswas

                                                              either 3 or 10 cm. Samples were dried at 60 C and cru-
                                                              shed with a mortar and pestle. Isotope samples were
           Methods                                            then acidiﬁed with 10% HCl to remove any carbonate,
                                                              dried again, and disaggregated.
           Sediment cores were collected in 1998 and 1999 at the  Carbon bulk and isotopic compositions were deter-
           locations shown in Fig. 1. One core (site 5, 7.9-m  mined using a Carlo Erba NC2500 elemental analyzer
           modern water depth) was collected from a dredging  coupled to a Finnigan Delta Plus isotope ratio mass
           barge using a crane to deploy a modiﬁed Mackereth-  spectrometer at the USGS facilities in Reston, Virginia.
           typepistoncorerconﬁguredto penetrateandrecover as  Calibration for the total organic carbon (TOC) deter-
           much as 12 m of sediment. The other two cores (site 1  minations was accomplished using the National Re-
           and site 6, at 25- and 26-m water depths, respectively)  search Council of Canada Certiﬁed Reference Material
           were obtained from the R/V  Marion Dufresne  with its  PACS-2, a marine sediment with values of 3.32 mass%
           Calypso piston corer conﬁgured to sample >20 m of  C and 0.27 mass% N. Carbon-isotope compositions
           sediment.Coringoperationsandthe physicalproperties  were measured on CO and are reported in the  d  nota-
                                                                                 2

 = Page 4 =


                                                                                                            191
           tion,aspermil( & )relativetoViennaPeeDeeBelemnite  (ICP-MS) using a Finnigan Element 2 instrument
           (VPDB). The  d 13 C values are calibrated on a scale  equipped with a Cetac Technologies MCN6000 desol-
           deﬁned by USGS-24 (graphite) with  d 13 C=–15.9 & .  vating nebulizer and an autosampler. Original sample
                                                      r
           Analytical precision is estimated to be ±0.2 &  (1 ).  concentrations were calculated from measured ratios of
             For authigenic rhenium analyses, dried and pow-  187 Re: 185 Re by the standard isotope-dilution formula.
           dered sediment samples ( 0.1 g) were leached with    Radiocarbon ages indicated for cores 1, 5, and 6

           1.5 ml 4 N Seastar HNO for one hour at room tem-   (Fig. 2) were measured by accelerator mass spectrome-
                                 3
           perature to extract authigenic rhenium. Sample vials  try(Colmanetal.2002).Ageswerecorrectedforsecular
           were centrifuged and the supernatant was ﬁltered using  variation using CALIB 4.1 (Stuiver et al. 1998). Car-
                                     l
           dedicated syringes and 0.45- m cartridge ﬁlters. The  bonate sample ages were reservoir corrected using a
           leachate was combined with 0.1 g of 1.8 ppb  187 Re-en-  standard marine reservoir age of 400 years veriﬁed for
                                                          ·
           riched spike solution, diluted with Milli-Q water 3–6 ,  Chesapeake Bay by analyses of archived oyster shells of
           and transferred to autosampler vials. Samples were an-  knownage(Colmanetal.2002).Calibratedradiocarbon
           alyzedbyinductively-coupledplasmamassspectrometry  ages are reported using ‘‘cal a’’ or ‘‘cal ka’’ notation,

           Table 1  Chesapeake Bay and               14                       a
                                                                           B P
           Delaware radiocarbon data  Depth below mean  C age  Analytical  Cal a . .  Cal error + Cal error–  Medium
                                    sea level (m)            error               (older)   (younger)
                                    Site 5, core RR98-9 (Colman et al. 2002)
                                    –14.4             5,340   40        5,690    100        90        Oyster
                                    –15.0             6,060   55        6,460    160       110        Oyster
                                    –15.9             7,180   40        7,640     60        70        Oyster
                                    Site 6, core MD99-2209 (Colman et al. 2002)
                                    –43.2             6,660   45        7,200    120        80        Oyster
                                    Chesapeake Bay entrance (Harrison et al. 1965)
                                    –21.0             8,135  160        9,073    362       442        Oyster
                                    Core MD99-2208 (Vogt et al. 2000)
                                    –17.8             7,740   55        8,505     95        95        Oyster
                                    Tangier Sound (Hobbs 1988)
                                    –15.3             7,390  115        8,195    194       196        Wood
                                    James Estuary (Ellison and Nichols 1976)
                                     –2.5             1,310  160        1,210    325       286        Basal peat
                                     –5.0             2,700  160        2,819    350       461        Basal peat
                                     –7.3             4,880  140        5,621    291       304        Basal peat
                                    Rappahannock Estuary (Ellison and Nichols 1976)
                                     –0.9              535    95         552     118       176        Basal peat
                                     –1.3              980    90         879     181       178        Basal peat
                                     –4.5             3,345  120        3,589    286       247        Basal peat
                                     –5.7             2,810  160        2,958    405       251        Basal peat
                                     –9.2             5,780  210        6,595    460       422        Basal peat
                                    Delaware radiocarbon database (Ramsey and Baxter 1996)
                                     –1.2             1,650   70        1,547    160       160        Basal peat
                                     –2.5             2,070   80        2,026    158       158        Basal peat
                                     –2.6             1,770   60        1,685    138       138        Basal peat
                                     –2.8             2,560   95        2,575    220       221        Basal peat
                                     –3.1             2,260   70        2,208    158       159        Basal peat
                                     –3.6             2,420   95        2,528    220       220        Basal peat
                                     –3.6             3,270   70        3,500    140       140        Basal peat
                                     –3.8             1,950   55        1,865    129       129        Basal peat
                                     –3.9             2,820   70        2,929    153       153        Basal peat
                                     –4.7             2,880   70        3,029    184       185        Basal peat
                                     –5.0             2,490   80        2,549    190       190        Basal peat
                                     –5.2             2,945   95        3,104    240       241        Basal peat
                                     –5.3             3,314   63        3,522    129       130        Basal peat
                                     –6.3             3,780  170        4,131    443       443        Basal peat
                                     –6.4             3,430   70        3,660    182       183        Basal peat
                                     –6.4             3,980  105        4,398    256       256        Basal peat
                                     –7.7             4,090  100        4,596    246       246        Basal peat
                                    –10.9             4,490   80        5,093    223       223        Basal peat
                                    –12.8             5,600  110        6,424    241       241        Basal peat
                                    –13.4             5,345  110        6,110    207       207        Basal peat
           a
           Ages and 2 r  errors recali-  –14.7        6,170  115        7,022    244       245        Basal peat
           brated using CALIB 4.3 for all  –20.8      7,500  135        8,243    252       253        Basal peat
           data except from Colman et al.  –26.3     10,800  300       12,561    851       851        Basal peat
           (2002),andDelawarebasalpeat

 = Page 5 =


           192
                                                                            n
           indicating years or thousands of years, respectively, be-  analyses(Fig. 2, =23between5and13 cal ka;Colman
           fore 1950 . . Other literature ages (Table 1) are either  et al. 2002). Here we focus on the interval from 6.5 to
                    A D
           (1) reported in the notation format in which they were  8.5 cal ka.
           published (cal a . .), or (2) recalibrated in the case of  One geochemical indicator which is sensitive to sa-
                         B P
           older ages using CALIB 4.3 and reported as ‘‘cal a’’ or  linitychangesistheconservativetraceelementrhenium.
           ‘‘cal ka’’also.Forrecalibrationofageswithoutreported  Rhenium is highly enriched in seawater relative to
           d 13 C values, estimated values of 0, –15, and –25 were  crustal abundances. Concentrations of dissolved Re in
           used for shell, salt-marsh peat, and wood samples,  river waters are typically at least an order of magnitude
           respectively.                                      lowerthanintheocean(Colodneretal.1993).Rhenium
                                                              is a conservative element in seawater, meaning that its
                                                              concentration is consistentfrom basin to basin andthat
           Results                                            its concentration varies linearly with salinity. In sedi-
                                                              ments,authigenicrheniumcontentiscontrolledbythree
           Geochemical data show consistent timing and patterns  factors in the Chesapeake system: salinity of overlying
           of environmental change in the paleo-Chesapeake in  waters,oxygenconcentrationandassociatedredoxstate

           spiteofwideseparationofcoresites( 100 km).Proﬁles  of sediments, and contributions from erosion of rheni-
           of authigenic rhenium, organic carbon isotopes, and  um-rich Miocene deposits in the area.
           TOC for the three long cores (8 to 21 m) are shown in  Authigenic rhenium in dried Chesapeake Bay sedi-
           Fig. 3A–C. Age and mass accumulation models for the  ments rose from low values around 0.2±0.1 ppb
           three cores were developed from extensive radiocarbon  (Fig. 3A),indicatingdepositioninfreshwaterconditions

           Fig. 3A–D  Plots of  A  authi-
           genic rhenium,  B  d 13 C org ,  C
           TOC, and  D  radiocarbon sam-
           ples for sites 1, 5, and 6

 = Page 6 =


                                                                                                            193
           (Colodner et al. 1993), to higher but ﬂuctuating values  a relatively small oﬀset between carbonate and bulk
           around 1.3±1.0 ppb, indicating deposition in estuarine  TOC ages (Colman et al. 2002), however, suggests that
           to marine conditions. This transition in the site 1 core  substantial oxidation of Miocene sediments took place
           occurred abruptly between 7.1 and 7.5 cal ka, after  during reworking; this would also strip residual authi-
           5,000 yearsoflowandstablevaluespriortothisrise.At  genic rhenium prior to redeposition. In addition, rheni-
           site 5 values rose more gradually, starting at about  um levels in freshwater sediments deposited before the
           8 cal ka,andreachedaplateauat2.1 ppbby7.6 cal ka.  change to brackish water (site 1 older than 8 ka) are
           They dropped at about 6.9 cal ka to values similar to  extremely uniform in spite of changes in sedimentation
           those recorded in the other cores, and then rose again  rate.Thisindicates thattheleachable contribution from
           later. The bottom of the site 6 core just reaches the  freshwater authigenic and/or reworked rhenium is low
           transitioninterval.Therheniumpatternissimilartothe  (average=0.19 ppb,  n =110) and constant (standard
           site 1 pattern of an abrupt rise, although there are only  deviation=0.04 ppb).
           two pre-rise or early-rise data points. The values fol-  As described above, the core from site 5 shows a
           lowing the rise are lower than at site 1, consistent with  transient  d 13 C peak as heavy as –19 &  centered at
           the expected lower salinity at this more upstream site.  7.1 cal ka. The organic carbon in these sediments is
             Measured  d 13 C of sedimentary organic matter from  more enriched in  13 C than even fully marine particulate
           two cores shows a change from typical terrestrial or  organic carbon. This suggests contribution of a source
           ﬂuvial values around –25 &  VPDB to more marine    of carbon which is isotopically unusually heavy. One
           planktonic values of –22 &  between 7.6 and 6.5 cal ka.  likely source would be salt-marsh vegetation reworked
           In one core (site 5) the value rose to a high of –19 &  at  and deposited as the intertidal zone passed through the
           7.1 cal ka, followed by stabilization around –24 &  paleo-elevation of the core site during inundation. Due
           by 6.5 cal ka. A coincident peak in TOC (3%) is also  to physiology which excludes salt, biomass from salt-
           seen in this core. No comparable  d 13 C or TOC anoma-  marsh plants such as  Spartina alterniﬂora  has been
           lies are seen in either of the cores from deeper water  showntohave  d 13 Cvaluesof–13to–10 &  (Haddadand
           (sites 1 and 6).                                   Martens 1987). The decline of the  d 13 C peak starting at
                                                              7.1 cal ka and continuing to around 6.6 cal ka is con-
                                                              sistentwithdrowningortransgressionofthemarshwith
           Discussion                                         rising sea level. Morris et al. (2002) suggest that salt-
                                                              marsh drowning typically occurs when sea-level rise
                                                                               –1
           Thegeochemicalresultsdescribedaboveindicateclearly  exceeds 12 mm year .
           thatarapidtransitionfromfreshtobrackishconditions    The  d 13 C peak at site 5 coincides with a TOC peak
           took place in Chesapeake Bay between 7.4 and       (3%) about three times higher than the typical value in
           8.2 cal ka. The speciﬁc mechanism, however, which  allcores(1%).Thisisalsoconsistentwithproximitytoa
           producedthisinitialchangeislessobvious.Thecauseof  salt marsh during deposition, even though peat as such
           the apparent, subsequent return to progressively fresher  was not recovered. Additionally, the site 5 core shows
           conditionsinthebay,basedparticularlyonfossiloyster  greater sedimentological variability over its length than
           occurrences described below, also requires an explana-  either of the deep-water cores, consistent with its loca-
           tion consistent with the ﬁrst mechanism and with other  tionrelativetotheshore.The  d 13 Cpeakoccurswithina
           data sets of eustatic sea level.                   sedimentologicalintervalin the core(Fig. 2)interpreted
             The geochemical proxies measured at the three core  as having been deposited in restricted estuarine condi-
           sites provide independent evidence of the timing and  tions (Baucom et al. 2001); such an interval is not well
           nature of ﬂooding of the paleovalley which became  developed in the site 1 and site 6 cores.
           Chesapeake Bay. The clearest evidence comes from the  Inthesite 5core,theintervalofthe  d 13 Cexcursionis
           rheniumdatainthedeeperwatercores(sites 1and6).In   underlainbyarticulatedoystershellsdatedat7.6 cal ka
           these locations, particularly at site 1, we interpret the  (Baucom et al. 2001; Colman et al. 2002) at a depth of
           rheniumsignalasbeingpredominantlydrivenbysalinity  about 16.5 m below modern sea level (Figs. 2 and 3B).
           changes,withanabruptshifttohighersalinityataround  The oysters overlie coarse ﬂuvial sand and gravel. This
           7.5 cal ka. This is also reﬂected to a lesser extent by the  oyster-on-sand contact marks the initial transition from
           d 13 C data, where the transition begins at around the  freshtobrackishconditionsatthissite.The d 13 Cpeakin
           same time but proceeds more gradually.             the site 5 core is bracketed above (15 m below sea level,
             Rhenium data for core site 5 are less clear, however,  m b.s.l.) by less concentrated oysters which give an age
           andappeartoshowaprimarysalinitysignalmodiﬁedby     of6.5 cal ka(Fig. 2).Aspartofanotherstudy,asimilar
           the reducing conditions developed in organic-rich sedi-  core was collected from a buried paleochannel about
           ments during an interval of salt-marsh deposition be-  midway between sites 1 and 5 in 10 m of water. This
           tween7.9and6.6 cal ka(seediscussionbelow).Another  core produced a basal oyster age of 8.2 cal ka for a bed
           complicatingfactorwhichcannotberuledoutatsite 5is  at 17.8 m b.s.l. (Fig. 4; Vogt et al. 2000). The basal age
           the addition of reworked rhenium from older Miocene  of the site 6 core, which penetrated the upper few cen-
           sediments. The essential absence of reworked organic  timeters of an oyster bed, is 7.6 cal ka at 43 m b.s.l.
           carbon,asindicated byconsistentradiocarbonagesand  (Fig. 2).

 = Page 7 =


           194
           Fig. 4  Comparison of sea-level
           data from Chesapeake Bay
           site 5 with data derived from
           corals (Lighty et al. 1982, ages
           recalibrated), basal salt-marsh
           peat from the Delaware radio-
           carbon database (Ramsey and
           Baxter1996;elevationsadjusted
           to depth below mean sea level
           using Lewes, Delaware tide
           gauge datum information), and
           other published Chesapeake
           Bay data (Table 1). The  dashed
           line  corresponds to the timing
           of the rapid sea-level rise event
           (CRE 3)proposed by Blanchon
           and Shaw (1995)





















             Extensiveareasoffossiloysterbedsolderthan3.5 ka  oyster and peat deposits in and around the bay do not
           are present in northernmost Chesapeake Bay and in  generallyindicatemeasurabledepressionbelowexpected
           upstreamareas ofa majortributary,the Potomac River  depths based on non-Chesapeake sea-level curves.
           (Callenderetal.1984;C.Judy,writtencommunication).    Published data from other Chesapeake studies con-
           Salinities are too low in these areas for modern oysters  strain sea level in areas beyond our immediate coring
           to survive (<11 ppt), indicating that saltwater intruded  region (Fig. 4, Table 1). Hobbs (1988) dated a piece of
           fartherupinto theestuaryanditstributariesinthe past  wood from a long core from the eastern side of the

           than it does at present.                           Virginia part of the bay (approximately 37 47.7N, 75
                                                                                                        ¢
                                                                 ¢
             The location of the estuarine mixing zone can be  51.7W) and obtained a  14 C age of 7.4 ka. The sample
           dated and mapped using occurrences of fossil oysters  was collected from below a fossil oyster reef at a depth
           such as those in Chesapeake sediments. Other estuaries,  of 15.25 m b.s.l., 15 cm above the basal Holocene un-
           such as Mobile Bay (Ryan and Goodell 1972) in Ala-  conformity. Ellison and Nichols (1976) cored and dated
           bamaandtheHudsonRiverestuary(Belletal.2000)in      peat in several Chesapeake Bay subestuaries, including
           New York, show similar patterns of upstream occur-  anunusuallythicksalt-marshpeatintheRappahannock
           renceoffossiloysters(>5.7and>6.2 ka,respectively).  Estuary (Figs. 1 and 4, Table 1). They obtained a ra-
           Younger fossil oysters are found progressively ocean-  diocarbon age of 6.6 cal ka for a basal peat collected
           ward in Chesapeake Bay and the other estuaries,    from 9.2 m below the marsh surface. Microfossils from
           tracking retreat of the mixing zone as ﬂuvial sediments  the site 1 core at depths up to 38 m b.s.l. indicate sev-
           ﬁlled the estuary heads during the period of relatively  eral, brief episodes of temporary saltwater incursion
                                       –1
           slow sea-level rise (<3 mm year ) which began around  may have taken place, starting as early as about
           6 ka.                                              10 cal ka (Willard et al. 2000), possibly produced by
             Eustatic sea-level change is an obvious driver of  storm surges. Sediments containing freshwater diatoms
           transition of coastal river valleys to estuaries during the  overlie each of these early brackish intervals.
           mid-Holocene. Sea level can be constrained from Ca-  The pattern of rapid advance of oysters upstream
           ribbean coral and basal salt-marsh peat from Delaware  followed by gradual retreat, as well as the abrupt
           (Fig. 4), along with Chesapeake Bay oyster and salt-  changes in proxy salinity indicators can be explained in
           marsh data spanning the interval of interest. Anoma-  severalways.Onescenariowhichisconsistentwiththese
           louslyhigh subsidencereportedfor the Chesapeake Bay  observations is the occurrence of a severe and extended
           region based on tide gauge data appears to be a rela-  drought. Decreased discharge of freshwater from tribu-
           tively recent phenomenon. Age-depth data for 7–8 ka  tarieswouldcauseintrusionofbrackishwaterintoareas

 = Page 8 =


                                                                                                            195
           which were usually fresh. Although such a scenario is  indicators. Taken in the chronological and vertical
           possible, the drought would need to be of considerable  contextofothersea-leveldata(Fig. 3),itisclearthatthe
           durationtomaintainthesituation;otherwise,thesystem  site 6oysterscannothavelivedclosetosealevel.Itmust
           would eventually revert to fresher conditions as the  also be true, however, that shallower oysters from the
           drought ended. No independent evidence of such a   other sites could have lived at some depth below sea
           drought has yet been reported. Data of Webb et al.  level. So, in the most conservative interpretation, they
           (1993) indicate a general increase in precipitation and  canonlybeusedtoconstrainlowerlimitsofsealevelat
           runoﬀ over the Holocene for the northeast U.S. This  the time of their formation. The fact that the transition
           could explain the seaward retreat of oysters instead of,  to brackish conditions in the deep-water cores (site 6
           orincombinationwith,sedimentinﬁlling attheheadof   and site 1) did not take place much earlier than the
           the estuary and in tributaries. Increasing precipitation  transition in the shallow-water cores presents an inter-
           alone,however,isunlikelytohavetotallysurpassedsea-  esting problem.
           level rise in Chesapeake Bay.                        The permanent fresh-brackish transition appears to
             AsecondexplanationfortheChesapeakedataisthat     have been delayed until sea level rose gradually beyond
                                                 –1
           sea level rose monotonically (<10 mm year ) but that  about18 mbelowmodernsealevel.Thiscorrespondsto
           the sea level crossed a break in slope (from steeper to  both the transition depth at site 5 and the depth of the
           ﬂatter) in the topography being ﬂooded. This would  modern rim of the relict axial basin in the Chesapeake
           produce acceleration in both areal and upstream extent  (Fig. 1). Because the thalweg of the Susquehanna pa-
           ofinundationwithnochangeinabsoluterateofrise.In    leovalley lies at more than 50 m.b.s.l. in Chesapeake
           combinationwiththetopographicthreshold,thesystem   Bay, this implies that a physical or hydrological barrier
           would have also surpassed a hydrographic threshold.  musthavebeenpresenttorestricttheinﬂuxofsaltwater
           Saltwater intrusionintoan estuary isa functionof both  untilafter8.2 cal ka.Thereisnoevidenceofanearlyto
           freshwaterdischargeintotheestuaryandcross-sectional  mid-Holocene sill between the modern bay mouth and
           areaoftheestuary(Savenije1993).Theexpansionofthe   site 1. Therefore, these data support the second expla-
           nascent Chesapeake beyond the conﬁnes of the narrow  nation above – sea-level rise passing a topographic and
           Cape Charles paleovalley of the Susquehanna River  hydrographic threshold – for the delay in transition to
           (Colmanetal.1990)wouldhavemarkedlyincreasedthe     brackish conditions. The narrow, pre-8.2 cal ka Chesa-
           cross-sectional area of the estuary without changing  peake would have functioned as a fjord-like and tidal-
           freshwater  discharge.  Crossing  this  hydrographic  fresh extension of the Susquehanna River until the
           thresholdwouldhaveresultedinextensiveandsustained  critical sea level was reached.
           upstream intrusion of saltwater. The oceanward retreat  Aﬁnalexplanationfortheadvance-retreatpatternin
           of oysters observed during continued but more gradual  oyster beds and the sharp geochemical transition is that
           rising of sea level since that time indicates that the sys-  theywereproducedbyasudden(<200 years)andlarge
           tem was re-establishing near-equilibrium conditions  (>4 m) jump in sea level – similar to that postulated
           which were swamped by an initial inundation.       from Caribbean relict-reef data by Blanchon and Shaw
             All Chesapeake cores described here show that the  (1995). Larcombe et al. (1995) reported evidence of a
           shifttobrackishconditionsaround7.4to8.2 cal kawas  sea-level rise of 30 mm year  –1  around the same time
           (1) virtually simultaneous (given uncertainties in mea-  (post-8.2 cal ka) in Australia. Most coral-derived re-
           surement, calibration, and reservoir correction of ra-  cords of sea level from the Paciﬁc Ocean, however, do
           diocarbon ages) over an upstream distance of at least  not show this event (e.g., Tahiti, Bard et al. 1996,
           100 km, and (2) permanent. The sustained transition at  Montaggioni et al. 1997; Papua New Guinea, Chappell
           site 1, based on geochemistry (Fig. 3) and microfossils  and Polach 1991), although the larger depth ranges of
           (Willard et al. 2000), began around 7.4 cal ka, or  Paciﬁc reef-crest corals may not be sensitive enough to
           35 m b.s.l. Oysters overlying the basal Holocene un-  register an event of less than 6 m (Blanchon 1998; but
           conformityorﬂuvialsedimentsintwocoresgavesimilar   see Montaggioni and Bard 1998).
           ages – site 5=7.6 cal ka, 16.5 m b.s.l.; core MD99-  Recently, Blanchon et al. (2002) have reported addi-
           2208=8.2 cal ka, 17.8 m b.s.l. (Vogt et al. 2000). The  tionaldiscoveriesofrelictreefsandsubmergedwave-cut
           base of a third core (site 6) which penetrated the top of  notches in the Caribbean which support and reﬁne
           an oyster bed presumed to overlie the basal Holocene  previousinterpretationsofameter-scalejumpstartingat
           unconformityorearlyHoloceneﬂuvialdepositsgavean    7.6 cal ka. A rapid-rise event at this time, although not
           age of 7.6 cal ka.                                 necessarily as large or as rapid, is also consistent with
             The site 6 basal oysters are approximately the same  data from the inner Atlantic shelf of the U.S. reported
           age as the other two basal oysters from shallow-water  by Thieler et al. (1999). Other indications of rapid or
           cores,buttheyarenotinterpretedassea-levelindicators  coincident sea-level rise may include catastrophic
           because they are found approximately 43 m b.s.l. or  ﬂooding of the Black Sea by overtopping of the Bosp-
           26 m below the level of oysters in the other cores.  orus spillway (‘‘Noah’s Flood’’, 7,150  14 Ca . .; Ryan
                                                                                                     B P
           This 26-m depth range for approximately contempora-  etal.1997;RyanandPitman1998;butseealsoAksuet
           neous oysters indicates that care must be taken in using  al. 2002), more gradual ﬂooding of Ancylus Lake to
           oysters from a setting like Chesapeake Bay as sea-level  form the Litorina/Baltic Sea (7,500 to 7,300  14 Ca . .,
                                                                                                           B P

 = Page 9 =


           196
           Bianchi et al. 2000; about 8,350 to 7,860  14 Ca . .,  Bianchi TS, Engelhaupt E, Westman P, Andren T, Rolﬀ C, Elm-
                                                        B P
           Sohlenius et al. 2001), and sudden transition from   grenR (2000)Cyanobacterial bloomsintheBaltic Sea:natural
                                                                or human-induced? Limnol Oceanogr 45:716–726
           restrictedtoopenestuarineconditionsinGalvestonBay  Blanchon P, Shaw J (1995) Reef drowning during the last degla-
           around 7.2 cal ka (Anderson et al. 2001). An anoma-  ciation; evidence for catastrophic sea-level rise and ice-sheet
           lously rapid rise is not required by the Chesapeake Bay  collapse. Geology 23:4–8
           data, but neither is it precluded.                 Blanchon P (1998) Comment: continuous record of reef growth
                                                                over the past 14 k.y. on the mid-Paciﬁc island of Tahiti; dis-
                                                                cussion and reply. Geology 26:479
           Conclusions                                        Blanchon P, Jones B, Ford DC (2002) Discovery of a submerged
                                                                relic reef and shoreline oﬀ Grand Cayman: further support for
                                                                an early Holocene jump in sea level. Sediment Geol 147:253–
           Geochemical and oyster evidence from both deep-water  270
           andshallow-watersedimentcoresconstrainthetimingof  CallenderE,CarterV,HahlDC,HittK,SchultzBI(eds)(1984)A
           the fresh-brackish transition in northern Chesapeake  water-qualitystudyofthetidalPotomacriverandestuary–an
                                                                overview. US Geol Surv Water-Supply Pap W 2233
           Bay to between 7.4 and 8.2 cal ka. This transition took  ChappellJ,PolachH(1991)Post-glacialsea-levelrisefromacoral
           place when sea level rose beyond about 18 m below    record at Huon Peninsula, Papua New-Guinea. Nature
           modern sea level, consistent with Caribbean coral data  349:147–149
           and Delaware basal peat data. The delay in saltwater  Colman SM, Hobbs CH III (1987) Quaternary geology of the
           intrusion into the bay may imply the existence of a to-  southern Virginia part of the Chesapeake Bay. USGS MF-
                                                                1948-A
           pographic and hydrographic threshold which was not  Colman SM, Hobbs, CH III (1988) Maps showing Quaternary
           exceeded by previous sea-level rise. Alternatively, the  geology of the northern Virginia part of the Chesapeake Bay.
           suddenchangecouldbeaccountedforbyarapidjumpin        USGS MF-1948-B
           sea level. It is notpossible to diﬀerentiate betweenthese  Colman SM, Mixon RB (1988) The record of major Quaternary
                                                                sea-level changes in a large coastal plain estuary, Chesapeake
           two mechanisms with the present data but additional,  Bay, Eastern United States. Palaeogeogr Palaeoclimatol Pal-
           detailed coring studies in Chesapeake Bay and other  aeoecol 68:99–116
           estuaries could distinguish between the twoscenarios.  ColmanSM,HalkaJP(1989a)MapsshowingQuaternarygeology
                                                                of the southern Maryland part of the Chesapeake Bay. USGS
                                                                MF-1948-C
           Acknowledgments  We thank the R/V  Marion-Dufresne  shipboard  ColmanSM,HalkaJP(1989b)MapsshowingQuaternarygeology
           scientistsandcrew;T.CroninandD.WillardofUSGS-Restonfor  of the northern Maryland part of the Chesapeake Bay. USGS
           helpful discussions and access to complementary data; C. Wilson  MF-1948-D
           andthecrewoftheM/V  ScuﬀyII ;L.BallandD.Schneiderofthe
           Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution ICP facility for analytical  Colman SM, Halka JP, Hobbs CH III, Mixon RB, Foster DS
           assistance, and S. Hart and G. Ravizza for access to laboratory  (1990) Ancient channels of the Susquehanna River beneath
                                                                Chesapeake Bay and the Delmarva Peninsula. Geol Soc Am
           space and Re spikes; G. Wandless and A. Johnson of the USGS  Bull 102:1268–1279
           stableisotopelaboratories;P.Baucom,J.Yonehiro,andT.Barber,  Colman SM, Baucom PC, Bratton JF, Cronin TM, McGeehin
           formerlyofUSGS-WoodsHole,forﬁeldandlaboratoryassistance;
           andJ.KingandassociatesfromtheUniversityofRhodeIslandfor  JP, Willard D, Zimmerman AR, Vogt P (2002) Radiocarbon
           contributions during barge coring operations. We also thank R.  dating of Holocene sediment in Chesapeake Bay. Quat Res
                                                                57:58–70
           Williams Jr., J. Donnelly, and P. Blanchon for feedback and  Colodner D, Sachs J, Ravizza G, Turekian KK, Edmond J, Boyle
           commentsondraftsofthis manuscript.Anyuseoftrade,product,
           or ﬁrm names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply  E (1993) The geochemical cycle of rhenium; a reconnaissance.
           endorsement by the US Government.                    Earth Planet Sci Lett 117:205–221
                                                              Cronin TM (ed) (2000) Initial report on IMAGES V cruise of the
                                                                Marion-Dufresne to Chesapeake Bay June 20–22, 1999. USGS
                                                                Open-File Rep 00-306
           References                                         Ellison RL, Nichols MM (1976) Modern and Holocene forami-
                                                                nifera in the Chesapeake Bay region. In: Proc 1st Int Symp
           Aksu AE, Hiscott RN, Mudie PJ, Rochon A, Kaminski M,  BenthonicForaminiferaofContinentalMargins,Halifax,Nova
             Abrajano T, Yasar D (2002) Persistent Holocene outﬂow from  Scotia, 25–29 August 1975. Part A. Ecology and Biology.
             the Black Sea to the eastern Mediterranean contradicts Noah’s  Maritime Sediments Spec Publ 1, pp 131–151
             Flood hypothesis. GSA Today 12:4–10              FairbanksRG(1989)A17,000-yearglacio-eustaticsealevelrecord;
           Anderson J, Rodriguez A, Fletcher C, Fitzgerald D (2001) Re-  inﬂuence of glacial melting rates on the Younger Dryas event
             searchersfocusattentiononcoastalresponsetoclimatechange.  and deep-ocean circulation. Nature 342:637–642
             Eos Trans Am Geophys Union 82:513, 519, 520      Haddad RI, Martens CS (1987) Biogeochemical cycling in an or-
           Bard E, Hamelin B, Arnold M, Montaggioni LF, Cabioch G,  ganic-rich coastal marine basin. 9. Sources and accumulation
             Faure G, Rougerie F (1996) Deglacial sea-level record from  rates of vascular plant-derived organic material. Geochim
             Tahiti corals and the timing of global meltwater discharge.  Cosmochim Acta 51:2991–3001
             Nature 382:241–244                               Harrison W, Malloy RJ, Rusnak GA, Terasmae J (1965) Possible
           Baucom PC, Bratton JF, Colman SM, Moore J, King J, Heil C,  late Pleistocene uplift, Chesapeake Bay entrance. J Geol
             Seal R (2001) Selected data for sediment cores collected in  73:201–229
             Chesapeake Bay in 1996 and 1998. USGS Open-File Rep 01-  Hobbs CH III (1988) Prospecting for fossil oyster shell in Chesa-
             194                                                peake Bay. Mar Mining 7:199–208
           Bell RE, Flood RD, Carbotte SM, Ryan WBF, McHugh C, Cor-  KerhinRT,WilliamsC,CroninTM(1998)Lithologicdescriptions
             mier M, Versteeg R, Chayes D, Bokuniewicz H, Ferrini V,  ofpistoncoresfromChesapeakeBay,Maryland.USGSOpen-
             Thissen J (2000) Hudson River Estuary Program Benthic  File Rep 98-0787
             Mapping Project. Final Rep New York State Department of  Larcombe P, Carter RM, Dye J, Gagan MK, Johnson DP (1995)
             Environmental Conservation, Lamont-Doherty Earth Obser-  New evidence for episodic post-glacial sea-level rise, central
             vatory, Palisades, New York                        Great Barrier Reef, Australia. Mar Geol 127:1–44

 = Page 10 =


                                                                                                            197
           LightyRG,MacintyreIG,StuckenrathR(1982)  Acroporapalmata  Savenije HHG (1993) Predictive model for salt intrusion in estu-
             reef framework: a reliable indicator of sea level in the western  aries. J Hydrol 148:203–218
             Atlantic for the past 10,000 years. Coral Reefs 1:125–130  Sohlenius G, Emeis KC, Andren E, Andren T, Kohly A (2001)
           Montaggioni LF, Cabioch G, Camoinau GF, Bard E, Ribaud-  Development of anoxia during the Holocene fresh-brackish
             Laurenti A, Faure G, De´ jardin P, Re´ cy J (1997) Continuous  water transition in the Baltic Sea. Mar Geol 177:221–242
             record of reef growth over the past 14 k.y. on the mid-Paciﬁc  Stanley DJ, Warne AG (1994) Worldwide initiation of Holocene
             island of Tahiti. Geology 25:555–558               marinedeltasbydecelerationofsea-levelrise.Science265:228–
           Montaggioni LF, Bard E (1998) Reply: continuous record of reef  231
             growthoverthepast14 k.y.onthemid-PaciﬁcislandofTahiti.  Stuiver M, Reimer PJ, Braziunas TF (1998) High-precision radio-
             Geology 26:479–480                                 carbon age calibration for terrestrial and marine samples.
           Morris JT, Sundareshwar PV, Nietch CT, Kjerfve B, Cahoon DR  Radiocarbon 40:1127–1151
             (2002)Responsesofcoastalwetlandstorisingsealevel.Ecology  Thieler ER, Schwab WC, Gayes PT, Pilkey OH Jr, Cleary WJ,
             83 (in press)                                      Scanlon KM (1999) Paleoshorelines on the U.S. Atlantic and
           Oppenheimer M (1998) Global warming and the stability of the  Gulf continental shelf: evidence for sea-level stillstands and
             West Antarctic Ice Sheet. Nature 393:325–332       rapid rises duringdeglaciation. In: ConfProc Non-steady state
           RamseyKW,BaxterSJ(1996)RadiocarbondatesfromDelaware:  oftheinnershelfandshoreline:coastalchangeonthetimescale
             a compilation. Delaware Geol Surv Rep Inv no 54 (updated  of decades to millenia. University of Hawaii, Honolulu, 8–12
             version of database available at http://www.udel.edu/dgs/rad-  November 1999, pp 207–208
             carbtab.html)                                    Vogt PR, Halka JP, Hagen RA, Cronin T (2000) Geophysical
           RyanJJ,GoodellHG(1972)Marinegeologyandestuarinehistory  environmentinChesapeakeBay:  Marion-Dufresne  sitesMD99-
             of Mobile Bay, Alabama. Part 1. Contemporary sediments. In:  2205, 2206, 2208. In: Cronin T (ed) Initial report on IMAGES
             Nelson BW (ed) Environmental framework of coastal plain  V cruise of the Marion-Dufresne to Chesapeake Bay June 20–
             estuaries. Geol Soc Am Mem 133:517–554             22, 1999. USGS Open-File Rep 00-306, chap 2, pp 18–31
           RyanWBF,PitmanWCIII(1998)Noah’sFlood:thenewscientiﬁc  Webb RS, Anderson KH, Webb T III (1993) Pollen response-
             discoveries about the event that changed history. Simon &  surface estimates of late-Quaternary changes in the moisture
             Schuster, New York                                 balanceofthenortheasternUnitedStates.QuatRes40:213–227
           Ryan WBF, Pitman WC III, Major CO, Shimkus K, Moskalenko  Willard DA, Vogt PR, Cronin TM, Verardo S (2000) Oscillating
             V, Jones GA, Dimitrov P, Gorur N, Sakinc M, Yuce H (1997)  relative sea level during the Early Holocene: the stratigraphic
             AnabruptdrowningoftheBlackSeashelf.MarGeol138:119–  record of  Marion-Dufresne  core MD99-2207 from Chesapeake
             126                                                Bay. Eos Trans Am Geophys Union 81(48):F616

 = Page 11 =
