<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<metadata>
	<idinfo>
		<citation>
			<citeinfo>
				<origin>Comprehensive Coastal Inventory, Virginia Institute of Marine Science</origin>
				<pubdate>November 2008</pubdate>
				<title>City of Portsmouth Access Structures (port_astru)</title>
				<geoform Sync="TRUE">vector digital data</geoform>
				<onlink>http://ccrm.vims.edu/gis_data_maps/shoreline_inventories/index.html</onlink>
				<ftname Sync="TRUE">port_astru</ftname></citeinfo>
		</citation>
		<descript>
			<abstract>Shoreline Situation Reports (SSR) were first generated by VIMS in the 1970's to report the condition and status of the shore lands.  The SSR series was published in hardcopy on a county by county basis for each Tidewater Virginia locality.  The reports were intended to assist planners, managers, and regulators in decisions pertaining to management of coastal areas and natural resources therein.  This Shoreline Inventory report continues a process which updates and expands the earlier reports.  Data collected reports conditions surveyed in the immediate riparian zone, the bank, and along the shoreline.</abstract>
			<purpose>To inventory Virginia's tidal shoreline condition.</purpose>
			<supplinf>There are three shapefiles that are part of the City of Portsmouth Shoreline Inventory database: port_lubc, port_astru, port_sstru. Port_lubc (land use and bank cover for the City of Portsmouth) is an linear shapefile containing data about land use, bank height, bank cover, erosion, and marsh,and beach status along the shoreline. Port_sstru ( City of Portsmouth shoreline structures) is a linear shapefile delineating hard structures in place for shoreline protection (breakwater, bulkhead, dilapidated bulkhead, groinfield, jetty, marina, miscellaneous, military wharf, seawall, shipyard, wharf, and riprap). Port_astru (City of Portsmouth  structures) is a point shapefile with locations of docks, dilapidated docks, outfall,  private and public ramps, and boathouses. The attributes of these three shapefiles are explained in the Entity and Attribute Information section below.</supplinf>
			<langdata Sync="TRUE">en</langdata></descript>
		<timeperd>
			<timeinfo>
				<mdattim>
					<sngdate>
						<caldate>6/5/2002</caldate>
					</sngdate>
					<sngdate>
						<caldate>6/10/2002</caldate>
					</sngdate>
					<sngdate>
						<caldate>6/11/2002</caldate>
					</sngdate>
					<sngdate>
						<caldate>6/19/2002</caldate>
					</sngdate>
					<sngdate>
						<caldate>7/9/2002</caldate>
					</sngdate>
					<sngdate>
						<caldate>7/16/2002</caldate>
					</sngdate>
				</mdattim>
			</timeinfo>
			<current>Ground condition at time of survey</current>
		</timeperd>
		<status>
			<progress>Complete</progress>
			<update>Unknown</update>
		</status>
		<spdom>
			<bounding>
				<westbc Sync="TRUE">-76.405557</westbc>
				<eastbc Sync="TRUE">-76.292935</eastbc>
				<northbc Sync="TRUE">36.898431</northbc>
				<southbc Sync="TRUE">36.799402</southbc>
			</bounding>
			<lboundng><leftbc Sync="TRUE">374767.333585</leftbc><rightbc Sync="TRUE">384657.312236</rightbc><bottombc Sync="TRUE">4073538.820187</bottombc><topbc Sync="TRUE">4084387.530666</topbc></lboundng></spdom>
		<keywords>
			<theme>
				<themekt>none</themekt>
				<themekey>Shoreline conditions</themekey>
				<themekey>Shoreline structures</themekey>
				<themekey>Riparian Land Use</themekey>
				<themekey>Shoreline Inventory</themekey>
			</theme>
			<place>
				<placekt>none</placekt>
				<placekey>Virginia</placekey>
				<placekey>James River</placekey>
				<placekey>Western Branch Elizabeth River</placekey>
				<placekey>Elizabeth River</placekey>
				<placekey>Southern Branch Elizabeth River</placekey>
				<placekey>City of Portsmouth</placekey></place>
		</keywords>
		<accconst>none</accconst>
		<useconst>These data should not be used for jurisdictional permit determinations beyond providing general shoreline condition or status information.  These data have not been surveyed to property boundaries.</useconst>
		<ptcontac>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntper>Marcia Berman</cntper>
					<cntorg>Virginia Institute of Marine Science  (VIMS)</cntorg>
				</cntperp>
				<cntpos>Director of Comprehensive Coastal Inventory Program  (CCI)</cntpos>
				<cntvoice>804-684-7188</cntvoice>
				<cntfax>804-684-7179</cntfax>
				<cntemail>marcia@vims.edu</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</ptcontac>
		<native Sync="TRUE">Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 2; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.0.1770</native>
		<natvform Sync="TRUE">Shapefile</natvform></idinfo>
	<dataqual>
		<attracc>
			<attraccr>The attributes were compared to original GPS data logs for accuracy.  Errors were corrected where noted.</attraccr>
		</attracc>
		<logic>Chain-node topology present.  Linear coverages were built for lines and point coverages were built for points.</logic>
		<complete>All shoreline of the City of Portsmouth that has a minimum depth of 2 feet at mean low water was surveyed.  Some shorelines are coded remotely if access was restricted due to depth.</complete>
		<posacc>
			<horizpa>
				<horizpar>Shoreline conditions were recorded with a GPS unit as the boat moved along the shoreline. Data were transferred from the GPS boat track to an existing digital shoreline coverage by projecting data to the shoreline at a 90 degree angle from the boat track. High resolution orthophotography was used as background imagery to aid in data positioning. Dock and boathouse point data were aligned with docks on the images. Land use features were placed along the shore so changes in land use were coincident with changes illustrated in the imagery. Positional accuracy for data that has been corrected with imagery is  .3 meters (equivalent to image resolution). Data not visable on the imagery (bulkheads, riprap, etc.) has a positional accuracy of  11 meters. Accuracy was determined by comparing digitally processed data locations to onsite GPS ground surveys collected at random.</horizpar>
			</horizpa>
		</posacc>
		<lineage>
			<srcinfo>
				<srccite>
					<citeinfo>
						<origin>Commonwealth of Virginia through VA Information Tech Agency  (VITA)</origin>
						<pubdate>2006/2007</pubdate>
						<title>Virginia Base Mapping Program Orthophotography and Digital Terrain (DTM)</title>
						<geoform>remote-sensing image</geoform>
					</citeinfo>
				</srccite>
				<srccontr>Imagery serves as a background in the map portfolios. Imagery is used to update land use and structure data as well as to remotely code areas not surveyed in the field.  The VBMP shoreline was also used and adjusted using the imagery where needed.</srccontr>
			</srcinfo>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Data were collected by a two-person field crew using hand-held GPS units and navigating along the shoreline in a shoal draft boat.  Features collected include land use, bank height, bank cover, presence of marsh or beach, shoreline stability, riprap, marinas, breakwaters, dilapidated bulkheads, bulkheads, groinfields, miscellaneous,jetties, docks, dilapidated docks, boat ramps, boathouses, military wharfs, wharfs, shipyards, seawalls, and  outfalls.  Point features  were surveyed with a six second observation recorded at 1 reading/second. Linear features were surveyed kinematically at a rate of one observation every 3 seconds.</procdesc>
				<procdate>2002</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Data from the GPS units were postprocessed on a PC with Trimble Pathfinder Office software. Postprocessing includes differential correction using base station data collected at the VIMS laboratory. Corrected data is converted to shapefiles for further processing.</procdesc>
				<procdate>2002</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Data processing of the new shape files occurs in the ArcMap environment.  Boat-track "arcs" were manually corrected to the base shoreline (VBMP).  Arcs were split and moved to locations on the shoreline perpendicular to the original locations on the boat-track.  Shoreline arc segments were coded, and the shapefiles were visually checked for attribute accuracy between coded shoreline and boat-track data.  VBMP imagery was used to validate arc locations that could be seen on the imagery (e.g. riparian land use).</procdesc>
				<procdate>2008</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Data processing of the new shapefiles occurs in the ArcMap environment.  Boat-track "points" were manually corrected to the base shoreline (VBMP).  Points were moved to locations on the shoreline perpendicular to the original locations on the boat-track.  Points were coded and the access structures (astru) were visually checked for attribute accuracy between coded shoreline and boat-track data.  VBMP imagery was used to validate point locations that could be seen on the imagery (e.g. docks and boathouses).</procdesc>
				<procdate>2008</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Using ArcMap, the VBMP imagery was used as a data source to code shoreline in areas inaccessible by boat due to water depth.  Imagery was suitable for coding not all, but certain features such as land use, docks, boathouses and some erosion control.  These "remote" coded areas were given the item REMOTE = 'yes' to distinguish them from data collected in the field using GPS.</procdesc>
				<procdate>2008</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Areas surveyed prior to image collection could be updated using the high resolution 2006 VBMP imagery in the background.  Certain features and attributes such as land use and structures could be detected and therefore digitally checked and updated as a quality control measure.  Using ArcMap 9.2, docks, boathouses, boat ramps, some erosion control, and new development constructed after the original survey were digitized and coded as item REMOTE = 'yes' to distinguish them from data collected in the field using GPS.</procdesc>
				<procdate>2008</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>A portfolio containing ten 1:12,000 scale plates was created for the City of Portsmouth. Each plate shows four maps: riparian land use, bank conditions, shoreline features, and natural buffers.   VBMP 2006 imagery is displayed in the background to provide users with additional information.</procdesc>
				<procdate>2008</procdate>
			</procstep>
			<procstep>
				<procdesc>Metadata imported.</procdesc>
				<srcused>C:\DOCUME~1\sharon\LOCALS~1\Temp\xml53B2.tmp</srcused>
				<procdate>20081107</procdate>
				<proctime>09424900</proctime>
			</procstep>
			<procstep><procdesc Sync="TRUE">Dataset copied.</procdesc><srcused Sync="TRUE">N:\cci\portfolios\portsmouth_portfolio\final_shapefiles\port_astru_f</srcused><procdate Sync="TRUE">20081110</procdate><proctime Sync="TRUE">11285700</proctime></procstep></lineage>
	</dataqual>
	<spdoinfo>
		<direct Sync="TRUE">Vector</direct>
		<ptvctinf>
			<sdtsterm Name="port_astru">
				<sdtstype Sync="TRUE">Entity point</sdtstype>
				<ptvctcnt Sync="TRUE">595</ptvctcnt>
			</sdtsterm>
			<esriterm Name="port_astru"><efeatyp Sync="TRUE">Simple</efeatyp><efeageom Sync="TRUE">Point</efeageom><esritopo Sync="TRUE">FALSE</esritopo><efeacnt Sync="TRUE">595</efeacnt><spindex Sync="TRUE">FALSE</spindex><linrefer Sync="TRUE">FALSE</linrefer></esriterm></ptvctinf>
	</spdoinfo>
	<spref>
		<horizsys>
			<planar>
				<planci>
					<plance Sync="TRUE">coordinate pair</plance>
					<coordrep>
						<absres Sync="TRUE">0.000000</absres>
						<ordres Sync="TRUE">0.000000</ordres>
					</coordrep>
					<plandu Sync="TRUE">meters</plandu>
				</planci>
				<gridsys><gridsysn Sync="TRUE">Universal Transverse Mercator</gridsysn><utm><utmzone Sync="TRUE">18</utmzone><transmer><sfctrmer Sync="TRUE">0.999600</sfctrmer><longcm Sync="TRUE">-75.000000</longcm><latprjo Sync="TRUE">0.000000</latprjo><feast Sync="TRUE">500000.000000</feast><fnorth Sync="TRUE">0.000000</fnorth></transmer></utm></gridsys></planar>
			<geodetic>
				<horizdn Sync="TRUE">North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
				<ellips Sync="TRUE">Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
				<semiaxis Sync="TRUE">6378137.000000</semiaxis>
				<denflat Sync="TRUE">298.257222</denflat>
			</geodetic>
			<cordsysn><geogcsn Sync="TRUE">GCS_North_American_1983</geogcsn><projcsn Sync="TRUE">NAD_1983_UTM_Zone_18N</projcsn></cordsysn></horizsys>
	</spref>
	<eainfo>
		<detailed Name="port_astru">
			<enttyp>
				<enttypl>port_astru</enttypl>
				<enttypt Sync="TRUE">Feature Class</enttypt><enttypc Sync="TRUE">595</enttypc></enttyp>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>FID</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Internal feature number.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv></attrdomv>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
				<attalias Sync="TRUE">FID</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">OID</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">4</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>Shape</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>Feature geometry.</attrdef>
				<attrdefs>ESRI</attrdefs>
				<attrdomv>
					<udom>Coordinates defining the features.</udom>
				</attrdomv>
				<attalias Sync="TRUE">Shape</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Geometry</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">0</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale></attr>
			<attr>
				<attrlabl>remote</attrlabl>
				<attrdef>coded in the lab using field data and VBMP</attrdef>
				<attalias Sync="TRUE">remote</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">50</attwidth></attr>
			<attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">pntstruc</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">pntstruc</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">String</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">25</attwidth><attrdef>Point features that include structures for accessing and observing the water as well as miscellaneous features (e.g. outfalls).</attrdef><attrdomv><edom><edomv>boathouse</edomv></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>dilapidated dock</edomv></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>dock</edomv></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>outfall</edomv></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>private boat ramp</edomv></edom></attrdomv><attrdomv><edom><edomv>public boat ramp</edomv></edom></attrdomv></attr></detailed>
		<overview>
			<eaover>Two other shapefiles combine with _astru to complete the City of Portsmouth Shoreline Inventory.   The complete set includes _lubc, _astru, and _sstru.  Attributes in the _lubc file include: FEATURE or land use which  contains the following values: agriculture, commercial, forest, grass, paved, residential, scrub-shrub, industrial, timbered, unknown and bare; HEIGHT is the bank height with 0 - 5 feet, 5 - 10 feet, and 10 - 30 feet, and &gt;30; EROSION or bank erosion can have the values: low or high or undercut; MARSH values are Yes(Erosion), Yes(No_Erosion), No, or a blank field; BEACH defines the presence and condition of the beach: Yes(Eroding), Yes(No_Erosion), No, or blank field;  COVER is bank cover and defined as bare, partial, and total coverage; and REMOTE refers to data gathered remotely: a blank value indicates the data was collected with the GPS unit, a "y" indicates that the shoreline attributes where determined from the 2006 VBMP imagery. Attributes in the _astru (access structure shapefile) are: PNTSTRUC contains access structures boathouse, dock, dilapidated dock, outfall, and public or private ramp; and REMOTE. Attributes found in the _sstru shapefile are: STRUCTURE (erosion control)with values such as breakwater, bulkhead,  dilapidated bulkhead,groin, jetty, marina, miscellaneous and riprap; and REMOTE.</eaover>
		</overview>
	</eainfo>
	<distinfo>
		<resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
		<distliab>The Comprehensive Coastal Inventory Program (CCI) at VIMS performs a service by distributing data generated by either CCI or public agencies which offer data without restriction or charge. CCI assumes no responsibility for data accuracy or precision, metadata completeness or correctness for digital information. CCI assumes no liability for misuse of any data which may arise as a result of any alteration, conversion, or combination with other data sources. As well, the timeliness and scale of these products must be considered when evaluating appropriate use.</distliab>
		<stdorder>
			<digform>
				<digtinfo>
					<transize>0.898</transize>
					<dssize Sync="TRUE">0.016</dssize></digtinfo>
			</digform>
		</stdorder>
	</distinfo>
	<metainfo>
		<metd Sync="TRUE">20081110</metd>
		<metc>
			<cntinfo>
				<cntperp>
					<cntper>Sharon Killeen</cntper>
					<cntorg>Virginia Institute of Marine Science  (VIMS)</cntorg>
				</cntperp>
				<cntpos>GIS Programmer</cntpos>
				<cntaddr>
					<addrtype>P.O. Box 1346</addrtype>
					<address>Greate Road</address>
					<city>Gloucester Point</city>
					<state>Virginia</state>
					<postal>23062</postal>
				</cntaddr>
				<cntvoice>804-684-7534</cntvoice>
				<cntfax>804-684-7179</cntfax>
				<cntemail>sharon@vims.edu</cntemail>
			</cntinfo>
		</metc>
		<metstdn Sync="TRUE">FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
		<metstdv Sync="TRUE">FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
		<mettc Sync="TRUE">local time</mettc>
		<langmeta Sync="TRUE">en</langmeta><metextns><onlink Sync="TRUE">http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html</onlink><metprof Sync="TRUE">ESRI Metadata Profile</metprof></metextns></metainfo>
	<Esri><CreaDate>20081110</CreaDate><CreaTime>11285700</CreaTime><SyncOnce>FALSE</SyncOnce><SyncDate>20081110</SyncDate><SyncTime>11291000</SyncTime><ModDate>20081110</ModDate><ModTime>11291000</ModTime><DataProperties><lineage><Process ToolSource="C:\Program Files\ArcGIS\ArcToolbox\Toolboxes\Data Management Tools.tbx\DeleteField" Date="20081110" Time="112015">DeleteField N:\cci\portfolios\portsmouth_portfolio\final_shapefiles\port_astru_f.shp structure N:\cci\portfolios\portsmouth_portfolio\final_shapefiles\port_astru_f.shp</Process></lineage></DataProperties><MetaID>{D7695E09-B104-47CD-A061-3F7604C98C95}</MetaID></Esri><dataIdInfo><envirDesc Sync="TRUE">Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 2; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.3.0.1770</envirDesc><dataLang><languageCode Sync="TRUE" value="en"></languageCode></dataLang><idCitation><resTitle Sync="TRUE">port_astru</resTitle><presForm><PresFormCd Sync="TRUE" value="005"></PresFormCd></presForm></idCitation><spatRpType><SpatRepTypCd Sync="TRUE" value="001"></SpatRepTypCd></spatRpType><dataExt><geoEle><GeoBndBox esriExtentType="native"><westBL Sync="TRUE">374767.333585</westBL><eastBL Sync="TRUE">384657.312236</eastBL><northBL Sync="TRUE">4084387.530666</northBL><southBL Sync="TRUE">4073538.820187</southBL><exTypeCode Sync="TRUE">1</exTypeCode></GeoBndBox></geoEle></dataExt><geoBox esriExtentType="decdegrees"><westBL Sync="TRUE">-76.405557</westBL><eastBL Sync="TRUE">-76.292935</eastBL><northBL Sync="TRUE">36.898431</northBL><southBL Sync="TRUE">36.799402</southBL><exTypeCode Sync="TRUE">1</exTypeCode></geoBox></dataIdInfo><mdLang><languageCode Sync="TRUE" value="en"></languageCode></mdLang><mdStanName Sync="TRUE">ISO 19115 Geographic Information - Metadata</mdStanName><mdStanVer Sync="TRUE">DIS_ESRI1.0</mdStanVer><mdChar><CharSetCd Sync="TRUE" value="004"></CharSetCd></mdChar><mdHrLv><ScopeCd Sync="TRUE" value="005"></ScopeCd></mdHrLv><mdHrLvName Sync="TRUE">dataset</mdHrLvName><distInfo><distributor><distorTran><onLineSrc><orDesc Sync="TRUE">002</orDesc><linkage Sync="TRUE">file://\\139.70.26.250\ccrm\cci\portfolios\portsmouth_portfolio\final_shapefiles\port_astru.shp</linkage><protocol Sync="TRUE">Local Area Network</protocol></onLineSrc><transSize Sync="TRUE">0.016</transSize></distorTran><distorFormat><formatName Sync="TRUE">Shapefile</formatName></distorFormat></distributor></distInfo><refSysInfo><RefSystem><refSysID><identCode Sync="TRUE">NAD_1983_UTM_Zone_18N</identCode></refSysID></RefSystem></refSysInfo><spatRepInfo><VectSpatRep><topLvl><TopoLevCd Sync="TRUE" value="001"></TopoLevCd></topLvl><geometObjs Name="port_astru"><geoObjTyp><GeoObjTypCd Sync="TRUE" value="004"></GeoObjTypCd></geoObjTyp><geoObjCnt Sync="TRUE">595</geoObjCnt></geometObjs></VectSpatRep></spatRepInfo><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20081110</mdDateSt></metadata>
