






                   Chesapeake Bay Watershed Land Cover Data Series (CBLCD) Overview

                   To better understand how the land is changing and to relate those changes to
                   water quality trends, the USGS funded the production of a Chesapeake Bay
                   Watershed Land Cover Data Series (CBLCD) representing four dates: 1984,
                   1992, 2001, and 2006. These data were produced by MDA Federal Inc., under
                   contract to the USGS and were derived from Landsat 5 Thematic Mapper and
                   Landsat 7 Enhanced Thematic Mapper satellite imagery. Each of the four
                   datasets consists of 16 land use and land cover classes (Anderson, et al., 1976).
                   The datasets are temporally comparable and encompass the entire Chesapeake
                   Bay watershed and most intersecting counties.

                   The 2001 dataset represents the base layer for the Data Series and is composed
                   of NOAA’s 2001 Coastal Change Analysis Program (CCAP) dataset in the
                   coastal and northern portion of the watershed coupled with USGS’ 2001 National
                   Land Cover Dataset in the western and southwestern portions of the watershed.
                   MDA Federal’s Cross Correlation Analysis (CCA) technique was used to produce
                   updates (yr. 2006) and retrospective updates (yrs. 1984 and 1992) to the base
                   layer. CCA identifies significant spectral changes between image pairs within the
                   range of spectral values for each land cover class identified in the 2001 base
                   layer.  MDA Federal used Classification and Regression Trees to assign land
                   cover classes to 1984, 1992, and 2006 pixels exhibiting significant deviations
                   from their 2001 expected spectral values.  MDA Federal used these methods to
                   develop the 1996 and 2005 land cover change datasets for the Mid-Atlantic
                   coastal area funded by NOAA CCAP.

                   Land use and land cover interpretations derived from Landsat satellite imagery
                   are based on the sun’s reflectance off the land surface, e.g., urban areas have
                   different spectral reflectance characteristics than forests and herbaceous
                   vegetation.  For this reason, the data most accurately represent land cover (e.g.,
                   tree canopy) compared with land use or management (e.g., forests and pasture).
                   Due to similarities in spectral reflectance characteristics, some land use and land
                   cover classes are easily confused with each other. For example, the spectral
                   characteristics of low density residential areas with mature trees may closely
                   resemble those of forests. Cropland, pasture, and large lawns also share similar
                   spectral qualities. Therefore, users should be cautioned against evaluating
                   transitions between cropland and pasture based on the CBLCD. Users should be
                   generally confident, however, that the overall spatial patterns of cropland and
                   pasture in the Bay watershed are accurate because the USGS and NOAA used
                   multi-season imagery to create the 2001 base layer and the data compare
                   favorably with county-level cropland and pasture acreage estimates reported in
                   the 2002 U.S. Census of Agriculture.

                   The USGS is in the process of interpreting and publishing statistics on the extent,
                   type, and patterns of land cover change from 1984-2006 in the Bay watershed,
                   major tributaries, and counties. The USGS will also be publishing land change

 = Page 1 =







                   forecasts based on observed trends in the CBLCD. These additional
                   interpretations, statistics, and datasets will be publicly released over the coming
                   year following publication.

                   The CBLCD raster datasets and metadata can be downloaded from:
                   ftp://ftp.chesapeakebay.net/Gis/CBLCD_Series/

                   For more information about the data, please contact Fred Irani at
                   firani@chesapeakebay.net     or  firani@usgs.gov


                   References:
                   Anderson, J.R., E.E. Hardy, J.T. Roach, and R.E. Witmer, 1976. A Land Use And
                   Land Cover Classification System For Use With Remote Sensor Data.
                   Geological Survey Professional Paper 964. A revision of the land use
                   classification system as presented in U.S. Geological Survey Circular 671.

 = Page 2 =
