<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?><record id="5418"><title>Application of geologic map information to water quality issues in the southern part of the Chesapeake Bay watershed, Maryland and Virginia, eastern United States</title><author> Lucy McCartan,  John D Peper,  LJoseph Bachman,  JWright Jr  Horton</author><author_affiliation>U.S. Geological Survey, Reston, VA, USA</author_affiliation><source>Journal of Geochemical Exploration [J Geochem Explor], vol. 64, no. 1-3 pt 1, pp. 355-376, Nov 1999</source><resource_location>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0375-6742(98)00043-0</resource_location><issn>0375-6742</issn><publisher>ELSEVIER SCIENCE PUBLISHERS B.V., AMSTERDAM, (NETHERLANDS)</publisher><abstract>Geologic map units contain much information about the mineralogy, chemistry, and physical attributes of the rocks mapped. This paper presents information from regional-scale geologic maps in Maryland and Virginia, which are in the southern part of the Chesapeake Bay watershed in the eastern United States. The geologic map information is discussed and analyzed in relation to water chemistry data from shallow wells and stream reaches in the area. Two environmental problems in the Chesapeake Bay watershed are used as test examples. The problems, high acidity and high nitrate concentrations in streams and rivers, tend to be mitigated by some rock and sediment types and not by others. Carbonate rocks (limestone, dolomite, and carbonate-cemented rocks) have the greatest capacity to neutralize acidic ground water and surface water in contact with them. Rocks and sediments having high carbon or sulfur contents (such as peat and black shale) potentially contribute the most toward denitrification of ground water and surface water in contact with them. Rocks and sediments that are composed mostly of quartz, feldspar, and light-colored clay (rocks such as granite and sandstone, sediments such as sand and gravel) tend not to alter the chemistry of waters that are in contact with them. The testing of relationships between regionally mapped geologic units and water chemistry is in a preliminary stage, and initial results are encouraging.</abstract><record_language>English</record_language><summary_language/><publication_year>1999</publication_year><publication_date>1999-11</publication_date><publication_type>Journal Article; Conference</publication_type><descriptors>Maps; Water quality; Watersheds; Denitrification; Rivers; Rocks; Sediments; Groundwater; Surface waters; Quartz ; Acid neutralization; Chesapeake; Geological map</descriptors><classification>EE 481.1 Geology; EE 405.3 Surveying; EE 445.2 Water Analysis; EE 444.1 Surface Water; EE 483.1 Soils and Soil Mechanics; EE 444.2 Groundwater</classification><last_update>1999-06</last_update><subfile>Environmental Engineering Abstracts</subfile><accession_number>0387779</accession_number><notes/><availability/></record>